<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Edicts upon the ordaining and establishing of a common-place, and jurisdiction, of the priors and consulls of the merchants of the citie of Roan. Together with the letters, pattents, and declarations of His Maiestie, since that time made with the approbations, and regulating thereupon ensuing in the court of Parliament of the same citie. / Translated out of French into English, for the benefit, and use of merchants. By Peter Mitton.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89190</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1159_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210084</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868915</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89190)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 251:E1159[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Edicts upon the ordaining and establishing of a common-place, and jurisdiction, of the priors and consulls of the merchants of the citie of Roan. Together with the letters, pattents, and declarations of His Maiestie, since that time made with the approbations, and regulating thereupon ensuing in the court of Parliament of the same citie. / Translated out of French into English, for the benefit, and use of merchants. By Peter Mitton.</title>
                  <author>Mitton, Peter, translator.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>216 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. and are to be sold by Peter Mitton, dwelling in Mark-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The merchants new royall-exchange.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb:15th. 1644"; the 5 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Roanne (Loire, France) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Henry IV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121272:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EDICTS UPON THE Ordaining and Eſtabliſhing of a
<hi>Common-Place,</hi> and <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> of the PRIORS and CONSULLS OF THE MERCHANTS Of the CITIE of ROAN.</p>
            <p>Together with the Letters, Pattents, and Declarations of His MAIESTIE, ſince that time made with the Approbations, and Regulating thereupon enſuing in the Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> of the ſame Citie.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for the benefit, and uſe of MERCHANTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Peter Mitton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> and are to be ſold by
<hi>Peter Mitton,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Mark-Lane.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121272:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121272:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Thomas Atkin,</hi> Lord Major; And the Right Worſhipfull, the Aldermen, his Brethren; And to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in generall of this Honourable Citie of LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Honourable, and Right Worſhipfull,</hi> &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas you have been pleaſed (for the great eaſe and benefit of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of this Honourable Citie) to imploy me for that purpoſe, to procure a Court of Merchants here, (as may appear by a Petition of all the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121272:3"/> in generall) which Court is the uſuall Cuſtome in <hi>France,</hi> (as appeareth by their own Printed Book for that purpoſe) which ſaid Book, after a long and diligent ſearch, I have with much labour and charge, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, and procured leave from the Parliament to Print and Publiſh. And I hope, what is done, will be to your good liking: And if the buſineſſe ſhall be proſecuted, ſo as to be wholly effected, I fear not, the reſult will prove it to be an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable indeavour, from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant <hi>Peter Mitton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="documents_related_to_the_Rouen_market">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:121272:3"/>
            <head>THE MERCHANTS New Royall Exchange.</head>
            <div type="charter__letter_patent">
               <head>His Majeſties Edict, for the ordaining, and eſtabliſhing (in the Citie of <hi>Roan</hi>) of a <hi>Common-place</hi> for Merchants, according to the Order of the Change in <hi>Lions,</hi> and the Bourſe in <hi>Thoulouze.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <signed>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ENRY By the grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <salute>to all manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what eſtate ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, greeting;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we have been heretofore informed, That our Citie of <hi>Roan</hi> is one of the beſt Towns in all our Kingdom, by reaſon of the ſcituation; commodious for all Comerce and Traffick, where divers Merchants (as well of this our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121272:4"/> Realm, as of many other Nations) do uſually hold an entercourſe of buying and ſelling, for the continuance and propagation; whereof there hath of late (by vertue of our Letters miſſive) been erected and eſtabliſhed in the ſame Citie, a <hi>Common Place for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and their Factors</hi> to aſſemble themſelves in, twice every day at the hours accuſtomed, to diſpatch their Affairs and Negotiations in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is accuſtomably uſed in the Exchange at <hi>Lions,</hi> and the Bourſe at <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> to the intent, that the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Commodities of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, may more readily be tranſported and exchanged away with thoſe which our own bringeth forth.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore known to all men, that we (through an Ardent zeal and deſire that we have to advance the generall good of our ſaid City of <hi>Roan,</hi> and to augment the Common benefit, and eaſe of all Merchants Negotiating there, and in all things poſſible to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie them, that they may not be diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and drawn from their Affairs and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121272:4"/> buſineſſe, into ſundry Courts and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions, (by means of Suites and variances ariſing at any time about their Traffick) by the deliberate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Privy Councell, (together with divers Noblemen and Princes of our blood) beſides other great and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable perſonages: Of our own proper motion, aſſured knowledge, and Royall Authoritie, have approved and confirmed, and by theſe preſents, do approve and confirm, the erecting and eſtabliſhing, of the ſaid <hi>Common Place</hi> in that our Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ratifying the ſame in all points, with the Exchange of <hi>Lions,</hi> and the Bourſe of <hi>Thoulouze.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We will and Ordain, and our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, that all Merchants, Factors, and all others of what Nation ſoever, may reſort themſelves in the ſame twice every day, at the hours ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed: And in their meetings ſhall freely uſe their Traffick, and paſſe their Buſineſſe, as well by Exchange, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, not onely in the ſame place, but alſo in any other whatſoever, <pb n="8" facs="tcp:121272:5"/> within the Liberties of our ſaid Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> when and where, they ſhall think good, with all aſſurance and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of their Merchandize; And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſuch Priviledges and Liberties, which Merchants Trading to our Towns of
<hi>Lions</hi> and <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> do enjoy and uſe, according to the grant of our Predeceſſours, Kings of <hi>France,</hi> and of us.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, We will and ordain, That the Merchants of the ſaid Town of <hi>Roan</hi> (frequenting the ſame place) ſhall every yeer, cauſe a generall meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Merchants in the Common-Hall of the ſaid Bourſe, or in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place in the ſame Town, and at ſuch time, as they ſhall think good; in which meeting, they ſhall chuſe out of the ſaid number, three Officers, <hi>viz.</hi> a Prior and two Conſuls, to remain in their Authoritie for one yeer, and ſo yeerly to be changed, and there new to be elected, according to the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary form of moſt voices; not onely the Merchants of the Town of <hi>Roan,</hi> but alſo the Merchant ſtrangers, being <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121272:5"/> to be preſent, and aſſiſtants in the ſaid election; which election and nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation being fully ended, the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls, ſhall have preſent power in them, to take notice, and to give judgement (between all men, of what eſtate, qualitie, or condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be) of all ſuites, controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and differences, touching matters of Merchandizing, or buying, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, in ſuch manner as the <hi>Conſervator</hi> of the Fair at <hi>Lions,</hi> and the Prior and Conſull at <hi>Thoulouze</hi> do, as well for Obligations, Bils of Debt, Receits, Blankes Signed, Bils of Exchange, Anſwers by Sureties, Aſſociations of Merchants, (either generall or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular) Aſſurances, Accounts, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portations, Bargains, and Partnerſhips, for matters aforeſaid, or any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto, with as full Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorite, Power, and according to the Judgements, and Condemnations, of the ſaid Conſervators of <hi>Lions,</hi> and the Prior and Conſuls of
<hi>Thoulouze.</hi> And that the Judgements, and Sentences, Decrees and Ordinances, Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121272:6"/> and Commands of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of <hi>Roan, proviſsionaries,</hi> or
<hi>definitives,</hi> (the word <hi>proviſsionaire</hi> or
<hi>interlocutor,</hi> ſignifieth, to lay down the Moneys) ſhall ſtand in as much force and effect, for any matter Judicially determined, as thoſe cauſes which the Conſervator of <hi>Lions,</hi> and Prior and Conſuls of
<hi>Thoulouze,</hi> and others of our Judges do decide: And the ſame ſhall be executed by our Serjeants and Officers, in ſuch manner and form, as they are in their behalf above named, either by committing to priſon, or by inflicting ſevere puniſhment, if it be ſo decreed and ordained: And to that end, ſhall our Meſſengers and Officers be bound to ſerve the executions: Our Jaylors and Keepers of our priſons, ſhall likewiſe be bound to receive and keep all ſuch priſoners, in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as if they were committed unto them, by our aboveſaid Judges, and under the like penaltie (if any eſcape happen) as they be bound to keep the priſoners by the Authority of the ſaid Judges; For ſo we have charged and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121272:6"/> commanded our Meſſengers, and other our Officers, Jaylors, and Keepers of priſons, upon ſuch penalties, as the caſe ſhall require, and according as by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall be ſet down and declared, without any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, according as the offence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſhall require.</p>
               <p>Moreover, we have granted, and do grant, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to take unto them, twenty of the ſaid Merchants, or more or leſſe, as they ſhall think reaſonable, to aſſiſt them in proceeding in their Judgements, in Cauſes of Merchandize, Bils of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, Aſſurances, and Differences, as aboveſaid; and to cauſe to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, their Sentences, Judgements, and Ordinances, of Conſignments, Proviſions, Seizing of Goods, and all their other Condemnations, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, or Appointments, to proceed therein by Out-cries, Proclamations, giving notice to themſelves, or leaving notice at their Houſes, by Proof, Sales, Depoſitings, Deliveries, and execution Definitive, as the Caſe ſhall require.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:121272:7"/>Likewiſe, we give them power, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the ſame Proceſſe, and to proceed therein, according to their Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as well in matters ſummarily, as by proviſion: As acknowledgement of Bils, Subſcriptions, and Letters of Exchange.</p>
               <p>And the like in Acts of depoſite conſignments, by one onely default of Appearance duly proved, by ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning the perſon at his Houſe, or fixing there a Copy of the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Proceſſe, in all places where it is lawfull to be done. And touching o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters, where two defaults ſhall be made, or ſummoned in perſon, they ſhall proceed, obſerve, and keep the courſe according to the Kings Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. And for all matters wherein they ſhall give ſentence of execution according to their knowledge, We will, and We do permit them (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is ſaid) to cauſe the execution to paſſe in all places under command, of Our Court of Parliament at
<hi>Roan,</hi> and in all other places of Our Kingdom, where need ſhall require: Without <pb n="13" facs="tcp:121272:7"/> any diſturbance, or let to be done, by any of Our Judges, Juſticers, or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, either againſt them, or their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties: Neither ſhall they let or hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er any Summons, or Arreſt, Writ, or Warrants, iſſued out by them. And to give their aſſiſtance in all Cauſes appertaining to their knowledge, touching matters of Traffick, and all things thereunto belonging, againſt all Merchants trading in our ſaid Citie of <hi>Roan.</hi> And as touching their Factors, Dealers, and Correſponders, of what quality ſoever they be, (ſent by them into divers Countreys, Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Provinces, as well within, as without Our Kingdom, Countreys, and Dominions, under Our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for the Cauſe of Traffick, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing, and doing of buſineſſe, and all other things thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.)</p>
               <p>We will and ordain, That they may be conſtrained to bring their Cauſes and Proofs, for all matters aforeſaid, before the ſaid Prior, and Conſuls, for the time now being, or that ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121272:8"/> execute theſe Offices: Be it either for the rendring of account, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of part, or of whole, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations in penalties, or other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnations for fines, for treſpaſſes, and of all other things that ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, concerning, and belonging to the trade of Merchandize, according as they ſhall demerit; Whereof We have permitted them, and do give them power to uſe the form, even as the ſaid Conſervator of <hi>Lions,</hi> Prior and Conſuls of <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> and others our Judges do. And to cauſe execution to be ſerved on the offenders, either by Arreſt, Attachment of Goods, and ſale thereof, or by impriſonment of the Parties condemned, even as they ſhall think good. Inhibiting all our Judges to preſume to take knowledge of any of their ſaid proceedings, or of any matter or plea thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Which Commanders, We will to be made known unto them, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom it ſhall appertain, by the firſt of our Officers, or Serjeants, that ſhall be required, whom We injoyn
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121272:8"/> to perform the ſame accordingly, to the intent, that all thoſe charges and extraordinary expences, which Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants may be put unto, in following their ſuites againſt their Factors and Correſponders, before many Judges, might by this means be utterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, We have permitted, and do give Authority to the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls, that all ſuch penalties of Moneys as by them ſhall be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon men for contempts, or any other offences, ſhall be forfeited, the one half to Us, the other half to the uſe of the ſaid Common Place, or Bourſe of <hi>Roan,</hi> for the uſe thereof; allowing them likewiſe, abſolute libertie and power, to chuſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point one Counſellour, and one At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney, who ſhall by all lawfull means, labour the benefit and advancement of the ſaid place, and ſhall defend the ſame; to direct their Proceſſe and Cauſes, as well before the ſaid Priors and Conſuls, as before all other Judges.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:121272:9"/>And to the end, that the Merchants may aſſemble themſelves, as well to conſult of their common affairs, as to appoint the ſaid Counſellour and Atturney, without being bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to Us, or to Our Judges for leave, when need ſhall require. Therefore all ſuch Judgements as ſhall paſſe before the Prior and Conſuls, being ſealed with their ſeals, and ſigned by a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter by them appointed, be it by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, ſale, diſpoſing of Goods, or otherwiſe, ſhall be held for reall and lawfull, being paſt in manner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; without any conſtraint to obtain our further permiſſion or liking, even according as was granted by Our moſt Honourable Father the King, unto the Merchants of Our Citie of <hi>Lions,</hi> by His Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; Given in the Moneth of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord, 1535. Reſerving unto Our ſaid Court of Parliament, at Our ſaid Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> for a laſt concluſion; and by appeal, the juriſdiction and knowledge of the ſaid diſcords and differences.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:121272:9"/>And to the end that all ſuch appeals as ſhall proceed, by reaſon of the Judgements and Sentences that ſhall be given and declared by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may be ſpeedily and without delay ended in our ſaid Court; We have ordained, and do ordain, injoyn, and command, all our loving and truſty Preſidents and Councellors, (holding our ſaid Court of Parliament) to appoint the ſaid Merchants, without delay, one day in every week, ſuch as they ſhall think convenient, to hear, determine, and diſpatch the ſaid Appellations, by order of Roll for that purpoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained. And in regard of the proceſſe by writing, there ſhall be an other Roll made apart, to the end, that the ſaid appeals may be ended in the ſame day, to avoid the prolonging of ſuites, to the ruine and conſuming of the parties. And to the end, that the ſaid place of meeting of the Merchants, twice a day, may be quiet, and without diſturbance; Our pleaſure is, and We do ſtraightly command, That none of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121272:10"/> our Serjeants and Officers, preſume to enter into the ſame place, nor to make any Arreſt (for any cauſe) of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever, during the time of thoſe two accuſtomed hours of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And if ſuch Arreſt ſhould be made during the ſaid hours; We have declared heretofore, and do declare at this preſent, the ſame to be void and of no effect, charging all our Judges, not to meddle therein.</p>
               <p>And as we are informed, that the Trade of
<hi>Aſſurances,</hi> is of late greatly advanced by the Merchants of the ſaid Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> (a work ſo honourable) that it doth even increaſe, and greatly advance the Traffick, and commerce of the ſaid Citie. We (to the end thoſe ſaid policies of the ſaid <hi>Aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and all other writings thereunto belonging, may receive full force) have permitted, and do permit that all Merchants frequenting the ſaid place, (both now and hereafter) to come to aſſemble themſelves at all times, when it ſhall be needfull, to chuſe and nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate according to the moſt voices, one <pb n="19" facs="tcp:121272:10"/> Merchant amongſt them (ſuch a one as they ſhall think meet, being a man truſty and expert in the knowledge of the Traffick of
<hi>Aſſurances</hi>) who ſhall make and regiſter the ſaid policies, whereunto the Aſſurers ſhall ſet their hands at all times hereafter in the ſaid place and liberties of <hi>Roan,</hi> when as it ſhall pleaſe the Merchants: Whoſe Office ſhall likewiſe be, to draw forth accounts of ſuch arrerages as ſhall happen, (being thereunto called) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving for his pains and time ſpent about the buſineſſe, of the ſame
<hi>Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances,</hi> according as it ſhall be thought meet by the ſaid Merchants: And keep a perfect and true Regiſter of the ſame
<hi>Aſſurances;</hi> To the which Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Copies thereof, and all other Acts and Writings by him made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matter of
<hi>Aſſurances,</hi> and by him aſſigned; We will and ordain, That all manner of credit ſhall be thereunto given, before all Judges, and others, to whom it ſhall appertain, without that any other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall have to do, or meddle in the <pb n="20" facs="tcp:121272:11"/> ſaid buſineſſe of <hi>Aſſurances,</hi> or any thing thereunto belonging, unleſſe he be before choſen and admitted thereunto, by the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, and by the ſaid Merchants as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid.</p>
               <p>And we do command, and do charge, all Perſons holding our
<hi>Courts of Parliament, Great Councels, Admirals, Vice-Admirals, Stewards,</hi> and their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties,</hi> and all other Judges and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers whom it ſhall concern, That you do cauſe to be read, proclaimed and regiſtred, this our preſent Will, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, Permiſſion, and Ordinance; and the ſame to be obſerved and kept by all them accordingly; That the Merchants may uſe and enjoy the force and benefit thereof, plainly and peaceably, without any contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Moreover, We do charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our <hi>Atturney General,</hi> that he doth withall diligence, cauſe all theſe things to be plainly and truly executed, and that he doth certifie us of his diligence ſo done: For ſuch is our pleaſure, for <pb n="21" facs="tcp:121272:11"/> that of our meer motion and power, we will have it done, notwithſtanding any Ordinance, Cuſtomes, Statutes, Priviledges, Commands, Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or Letters to the contrary, the which in this cauſe, without doing prejudices to other cauſes, we have made void, and do hereby make void. And becauſe men ſhall have occaſion to uſe this our Grant in divers places; Our pleaſure is, That credit ſhall be given, to all ſuch Copies, as ſhall be made by any of our loving and truſty Notaries, and Secretaries, or under our Royall Seal, in as ample a manner as to the Originall.</p>
               <p>And to this effect, We do give you full Power, Authority, Commiſſion, and ſpeciall charge; commanding by theſe preſents, all our Juſtices, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and Subjects, to obey you in this caſe. And to the end this may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main eſtabliſhed for ever, (our own right in all other cauſes reſerved,) we have hereunto cauſed our Seal to be put. Given at
<hi>Paris,</hi> in the Moneth of <hi>March,</hi> and in the yeer of our Lord,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121272:12"/> 1556. And the tenth yeer of our Reign, and ſigned by the King, then in Councell, and ſealed with Green Wax, upon a Pendant of Red and Green Silk Lace.</p>
               <div type="rationale">
                  <head>A Reaſon wherefore this ancient Authority was granted to Merchants.</head>
                  <p>THere be two things that cauſe a Common-wealth to flouriſh, and are main Supporters and Pillars to the ſame: The Traffick and uſe of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandizing is the firſt; For by it, thoſe commodities, which in ſome Countries grow ſuperfluous, and over abundant, are tranſported over into others; In whoſe ſtead, the needfull commodities of thoſe other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms are returned thither. For which cauſe, the Emperour commanded all his Judges, and Governours of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, to hold the ſame in great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. The ſecond, is the order and cuſtome of Exchange, whereby any mans need may be ſupplied in all <pb n="23" facs="tcp:121272:12"/> places whereſoever, onely by a Bill of Exchange (of a Merchant of credit) without endangering either his goods or perſon; A thing moſt profitable as reporteth <hi>Papinian:</hi> So that the ancient Law-makers (perceiving that Merchants were the firſt ſetters up and inventors of Comerce, for buying and ſelling, together with the order and uſe of Exchange; and that they had thereof the beſt and ſoundeſt underſtanding, did wiſely inſtitute them onely to be the principall Judges thereof; whereby it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be no new Authority, whoſe beginning grew up, even with the beſt governed Common-wealths; As may be proved by infinite examples both of Greeks and Latines.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="ordinances">
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121272:13"/>
                  <head>The number of Officers, appertaining to the ſaid Juriſdiction, and of their Power.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THere is one Prior, and two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, called by thoſe Titles, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Kings pleaſure, being renewed every yeer, about Twelf-tide, at which time all the Merchants (as well Citizens as Strangers) are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in one place; where after they have given praiſe to God, choice is made of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, by moſt voices; In which election, every Merchant hath his voice, according to the number of Magiſtrates whom they are to chooſe: The manner of giving their voices, being done ſecretly, either in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or refuſall, of thoſe that are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated. As firſt, for the Prior, then for the firſt Conſull, and next for the ſecond Conſull; and ſo give they the <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121272:13"/> ſame to the Regiſter of their Court. And whoſoever hath the moſt voyces in the Election of the Prior, is Prior: and ſo conſequently for the Conſuls: Following orderly, the choiſe of the firſt, and next after the ſecond: being a thing moſt commendable and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for the avoyding of all affection and corruption. The Preſident where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being taken from the Greeks, who by the ſame courſe did make choiſe of their Magiſtrates and Governours.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Item, The Prior and Conſulls new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen, do take their oath of the old ones, and immediatly being ſet in the manner and form of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, they take the ſame oath, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all the Merchants there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled; promiſing duely and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to execute Juſtice, without any regard either to poor or rich, as other Judges do, when they are newly eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in their government.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:121272:14"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, preſent, or to be choſen hereafter, may call unto them, twenty Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, or a greater number to aſſiſt them, as Councellours, for the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and deciding of all ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, as appertain to their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: and to urge the ſaid Merchants thereunto, upon their oathes: in ſuch ſort, as other Judges do (with ſuch Councellours as they make choiſe of, to aſſiſt them) in like caſe; in regard of their Authority.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Priors and Conſuls, may chooſe and nominate one Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour, and one Atturney, to procure the good and maintenance of the ſaid <hi>Common Place,</hi> and to defend the ſame in all rightfull cauſes, and to mannage both the ſuits, buſineſſes, profits, revenues of the ſame place, as well before the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, as before all other Judges where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:121272:14"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Councellour and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney, ſhall be choſen by the moſt voyces of all the Merchants aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together for that purpoſe, and not at the will and pleaſure of the Prior and Conſuls: and are to be changed every year, according to the will and diſcretion of the ſame Merchants of the ſame place; having taken a generall deliberation thereof, according to the tenure of the ſaid Letters Patents of the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> the Kings pleaſure being well underſtood.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, ſhall take the oaths of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour and Atturney, that they ſhall procure as well the good and profit of the ſame place, as the credit and increaſe of their Authority, and the ſame ſhall defend againſt all men: And they ſhall never give counſell to the contrary, by any meanes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="article">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:121272:15"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Item, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may call to their aſſiſtance, the ſaid Counſellour and Atturney, that with them and the ſaid other Merchants, they may judge and decide all ſuites and differences appertaining to their knowledge.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Item, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, of their own authority, may appoint ſuch a Regiſter, as they ſhall think meet, to keep their Regiſters, who ſhall be changeable every year, as are the Prior and Conſuls; The which Regiſter ſhall ſubſcribe to all Acts that ſhall paſſe during their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by him done, under the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of a Regiſter, As is contained in the Letters Patents of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Item, all Meſſengers, and ſuch like Officers of the Kingdome, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained <pb n="29" facs="tcp:121272:15"/> by the King, to obey the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and duely and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to execute, all, and every of their Commands, Commiſſions, Sentences, either definitive or otherwiſe; And all the judiciall Acts and Decrees, of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, in every place of the Kingdom, like as of the Judges in all other Governments, whereas the ſaid Meſſengers and like Officers, do exerciſe their Offices; And under the ſame penalties to be laid upon them without default, like as they may be conſtrained to obey other Judges, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item.</hi> All Jailors and Keepers of Priſons, are ſubject to receive and keep the priſoners committed unto them by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as they do the priſoners of all the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Judges, and under the ſame pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties and bonds, if any eſcape happen, even like as they are ſubject <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121272:16"/> to keep the priſoners by Authority of the other Judges of the Kingdom, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The Kings pleaſure is, that all the ſaid Meſſengers and ſuch like Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; And all Jaylors and Keepers of Priſons within all his Dominions, ſhall obey the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, without demanding leave or other Licence of other Iudges, within whoſe government they do dwell, and exerciſe the charge of their Office, according as the late King <hi>Francis</hi> (of noble memory) hath granted to the Conſervator of the Fairs of <hi>Lion,</hi> in the Moneth of
<hi>February,</hi> in the yeer of our Lord God, 1535. As in the like Authority, the Prior and Conſuls of the Bourſe of <hi>Thoulouze</hi> have been eſtabliſhed by this King preſent, as is contained in the Letters Pattents hereafter ſpecified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="article">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:121272:16"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The Kings pleaſure is, and he doth permit and ſuffer the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to make choice, and to appoint, within all the Towns, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and other places of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of
<hi>Languedock</hi> and <hi>Lorogois,</hi> certain good, faithfull, and expert men, to ſearch all the Merchandizes, which is growing and uſed in the ſaid Provinces, to ſee if there be any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, fraud, falſification, or other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in any of the ſaid Merchandizes: And according to the report of the ſaid Searchers, to puniſh the offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, according to their demerits, and power of their authority, for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the ſaid Merchandizes, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may appoint one or more, Viſitors or Searchers, for the aboveſaid Cauſes, in all places where as they ſhall think <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121272:17"/> meet, for the true maintenance of all Merchandizes: And the ſaid Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſo appointed, ſhall take their oaths in all things requiſite, to diſcharge their Offices faithfully, and truly, and according to a good conſcience: And to ſearch the ſaid Merchandize, whereof, and by whom they ſhall be required accordingly, for the reſpects contained in the former Article: And the charges that ſhall ariſe, to be laid upon the offenders, according to the report of the ſaid Searchers, to whom the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall ſet down a reaſonable Salary, or reward, to be preſently paid unto them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any delay; to the end, not to fear the parties offending, by colour of ſuite, as the Kings pleaſure is, in the ſaid Letters, Pattents, of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may appoint the ſaid Searchers to take view of all Woods, Saffrons, Wools, and all other Merchandize that ſhall <pb n="33" facs="tcp:121272:17"/> be growing, and uſed in the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Languedock</hi> and <hi>Lorogois,</hi> as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Viſitors or Searchers, being choſen as before is ſaid, ſhall be ſubject upon any ſummons or requeſt made unto them, by any Merchant that pretendeth any Merchandizes to be falſified, or any other deceit to be found in it, that they ſhould execute their Offices, be it either in the Kings name, or in the name of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, without other expreſſe Commandment from the ſaid Prior and Conſuls; And ſhall duly and truly ſearch the Merchandize where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they ſhall be required, upon the like fines and forfeitures, as ſhould have been laid upon him, who by their report ſhould have been found culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to the end, that the parties offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhould not be made afraid by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, nor no other means uſed in the other Juriſdictions, for the gain and <pb n="34" facs="tcp:121272:18"/> profit of the Judges and their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, conſidering that the ſaid Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall be choſen and conſtituted, as before is ſaid.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Searchers may (in the Kings Name, and in the name of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls) command every man whom it ſhall concern, to bring forth all their Merchandizes, which they ſhall be required to ſearch, that they may truely diſcharge their Office: And if any man ſhall in ſuch caſe, refuſe to bring forth his Goods, they ſhall ſummon them (ſo refuſing) to appear before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, that they may take order therein according to reaſon.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls may puniſh ſuch as ſhall cauſe any Merchandizes to be ſearched, if by the Viſitors the ſame Merchandizes ſhall be found good and lawfull; as contrarywiſe, they may puniſh the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers, <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121272:18"/> or them that have committed any fault in their Merchandizes, in ſuch penalties as the caſe ſhall require, and as their authority may uſe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Forfeitures and Puniſhments, and what Seal the ſaid Prior and Conſuls may uſe.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to entertain, conſerve, and defend their Authority, may for every offence uſe onely the penalty and forfeitures of Money, and ſhall apply the ſame, the one half for the King, the other half to the party, according to his deſert; as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item.</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls may without diſperſing of the Goods, proceed by Sequeſtration, Arreſt and Impriſonment of the Perſons, <pb n="36" facs="tcp:121272:19"/> who by them ſhall be condemned, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their ſentence be fully executed, according to ſuch form and order, as the Conſervator of the Fairs of <hi>Lion, Bry,</hi> and
<hi>Champaign</hi> do uſually obſerve, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>February</hi> hereafter expreſſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> To give force and authority to all the Judiciall Acts (being done by the authority of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls) the ſame ſhall be ſealed with the Arms and Seal of the ſaid Prior, or of one of the ſaid Conſuls, who hath judged the ſaid Acts; and the ſame ſhall be ſubſcribed by their Regiſter, even as it is more amply expreſſed, in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> being thereby prohibited to uſe any of the Kings Seals, according to the tenour of the ſaid Letters.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, having knowledge of any fraud, or <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121272:19"/> other deceits, to be uſed by any man, they may cauſe the body of the offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be committed, and proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the offender, ſo far as his offence ſhall concern Trade of Merchandize, Change, or Rechange, although the King be intereſſed therein; Provided, that they proceed no further, then concerneth matters of Merchandizes, Change, and Rechange: And for his other puniſhment, for other offences, they ſhall deliver the perſons to the Judges, to whom doth appertain the knowledge thereof, for the better puniſhing of the offender, and the correcting of all other vices, and not otherwiſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Judgements of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may be executed throughout all the Kings Dominions, be it by Attachment of Goods and ſale thereof, Arreſt, and Impriſonment of the perſons condemned, as alſo by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties and forfeitures of Money, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cauſe of the offence, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:121272:20"/> and the Authority of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Judgements, Sentences, Ordinances, Commiſſions, Decrees and Commandments, as well defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive as otherwiſe, being done and judged by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, for all matters pertaining to their knowledge are of effect and force through all the Kings Dominions, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents in the Moneth of
<hi>May;</hi> and others of the Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> hereafter ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified according to the order, as well of the Conſervator of
<hi>Lion,</hi> as of other Judges.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:121272:20"/>
                  <head>Who are ſubject to the Authority of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and who are exempt.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> All Noble perſonages and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, all ſpirituall men, and lay-men, of age, or under age, or their deputies, uſing and exerciſing the Trade of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize or Exchange, ſhall in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect be ſubject to the power and authority of the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, without any manner of excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> and the Reſtrictions thereof, contained in the Letters Pattents, Given at <hi>Fountain Bleau,</hi> the ſeventh of <hi>December,</hi> in the yeer 1551. and publiſhed in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> the ninth of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> in the ſame yeer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Servants, Factors, Dealers, and others, of what quality ſoever <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121272:21"/> they be, being ſent by the Merchants of the ſaid <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> into any place, Countreys, Dominions, or Provinces, being either within or without the Kings Dominions, for the Trade of Merchandizes or Exchanges, are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the authority of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, onely in the reſpect of the Trade of Merchandize and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change. And all other Judges are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden concerning ſuch debates and differences, growing between the ſaid Merchants, and the parties above ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in this Article, onely to avoid the frauds, abuſes, and ill demeaners of the ſaid ſervants and dealers, and for other good reaſons, contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All the Heirs of ſuch men, as are ſubject to the ſaid authority of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and by them ſhall be arreſted and impriſoned, are exempted: And the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall not have to do, to arreſt <pb n="41" facs="tcp:121272:21"/> the bodies of the ſaid Heirs, but the ſame ſuite ſhall proceed before the Lords of the Court of Parliament of the ſaid <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> according to the effect of the Letters of the eight day of <hi>March,</hi> in the yeer 1551. grounded as well by common reaſon of Right, as by the Kings Ordinances in the
<hi>Rew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> of Letters Obligatories.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Noble perſonages, Lawyers and Officers, are exempt from the ſaid authority, although they have bought Cloath of what kinde ſoever, borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Money, or other Merchandizes for their neceſſary uſes, according to their eſtate and callings, as is contained in the reſtraints of the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Oppoſers againſt the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and Decrees of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, are exempt from the ſaid authority, and they cannot thereby be conſtrained to bring their cauſes of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121272:22"/> oppoſition before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls; but they ſhall return the ſame unto the Judges, to whom the knowledge thereof doth appertain; who having heard the ſame, and given ſentence thereof, and the execution being accompliſhed, both for the right of the King, and the performance of Juſtice, or otherwiſe ordained by the Judge, to whom the knowledge of the ſaid oppoſitions doth appertain, as is contained in the Reſtraints of the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Appeals of the Sentences and Ordinances of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, ſhall be brought immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Court of Parliament of the ſaid <hi>Thoulouze;</hi> And none other Judge can reform the Judgements of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as is contained in the Letters of the Moneth of <hi>July,</hi> 1549. and of the moneth of
<hi>May,</hi> 1551.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:121272:22"/>
                  <head>Three Additions to reſolve two difficulties.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> All that be exempted from the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, can by no means ſubmit themſelves thereunto, to take any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereof, unleſſe it be by the Kings expreſſe Command, or Conſent of the other Judges, in ſpeciall favour and regard of the Cauſes of the ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptions, wherein the ſaid Prior and Conſuls muſt be wiſe and carefull, not to give other Judges occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence by their raſh hearings.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Saving and excepting the Heirs of ſuch as be dead, that were in their life time ſubject to the ſaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, which Heirs (the debts owing by their Predeceſſors being proved, and they ſubmitting themſelves again by new Obligations to the rigor of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121272:23"/> ſaid Authority) may be conſtrained by arreſt and impriſonment of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: Renouncing the priviledges of the ſame Articles, made onely in the favour of the ſaid Heirs; As by the ſaid Article before alleadged doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Excepting the Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of Merchants, frequenting the ſame Bourſe, who, of what eſtate, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, or quality ſoever they be, either Noble or Head-Officers of the ſaid Citie of <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> or of any other condition, not uſing nor profeſſing the Trade of Merchandizing or Exchange, ſhall be ſummoned, adjourned, and purſued by all due wayes, and fit courſes, even as their Predeceſſors, Merchants ſhould have been, if they had lived before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, for all things concerning the Trade of Merchandize, and matters of Exchange, done and uſed by their ſaid Predeceſſors, Merchants, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending or alleaging any diſability or <pb n="45" facs="tcp:121272:23"/> inſufficiency, by reaſon of their Eſtate. Provided alwayes, that the ſuing of them ſhall be done, without arreſting or impriſoning of their perſons; And the ſaid Heirs (of what condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be) may ſue, or cauſe to be ſued, all other Merchants for the cauſes and reaſons before rehearſed, before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and no where elſe, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> and as in all common right is obſerved.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What matters are ſubject to the ſaid Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and what matters are not.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> All debates and differences, by reaſon of Traffick and dealing in Merchandize, or cauſe of Exchange, be it by Obligation, Bill of debt, Receits, Blanks ſigned, Letters of Exchange, and Rechange, Suretiſhips, Partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, (generall or particular) nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſufficiency of men, or <pb n="46" facs="tcp:121272:24"/> places where they dwell, Debts, Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, Accounts, or Auditings of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, Tranſports, Bargains, and all other Acts and things, with their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and what elſe belonging unto them, do appertain to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The Impoſition or Aſſeſſement of ſuch neceſſary ſums of Moneys, as ſhall be need full for the building, buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or hiring of a place fit for the exerciſes of the ſaid Juriſdiction to be uſed in, and for the profit of the ſaid common Bourſe, and of all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing thereunto, as alſo for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining (in good eſtate and due form) for the caſe and benefit of the tranſportation of all Merchandize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rivers of <hi>Garona,</hi> and
<hi>Geronda,</hi> from the ſaid City of <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> to the City of
<hi>Burdeaux,</hi> and of all other Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers within the Countreys of
<hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> and <hi>Lorogois:</hi> Alſo the Taxation
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121272:24"/> and Aſſeſſement of every Merchant (as well Inhabitant as Stranger, uſing the Trade of the <hi>Thoulouze</hi>) according to their Abilities and Dealings, doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may impoſe penalties of Money, upon all ſuch Merchants as ſhall obſtinately refuſe to pay ſuch ſums of Money as are taxed upon them for the Cauſes aboveſaid by the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, and their Councell: And ſhall conſtrain them thereunto, by all due wayes, and lawfull means, and alſo by impriſonment of their perſons, untill ſuch time as they ſhall make payment of the Moneys impoſed upon them, as aforeſaid. And the penalties that ſhall grow thereupon, ſhall be diſpoſed of by the Prior and Conſuls, the one half for the King, the other half for the benefit of the ſaid Bourſe, as is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:121272:25"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> There doth appertain to the ſaid Juriſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, the knowledge of rendering of accounts, payments of the whole, or of part, and all other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Trade of Merchandize, and order of Exchange, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The puniſhing of all frauds, abuſes, deceits, falſifications, and all other ill dealings in Merchandizes, bought and uſed in the ſaid Countreys of <hi>Languedock</hi> and
<hi>Lorogois:</hi> And all abuſes committed in the courſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes: All this, in all reaſon, doth appertain to the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, as is contained in the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121272:25"/>
                  <head>Matters wherein the Prior or Conſuls, are forbidden to deal withall.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> all matters criminall or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, in regard whereof the Kings Atturney is a party, and thereby hath intereſt therein; as falſifying of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and Bills of debt, or other writings, matters of reproach or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit of perſons, thefts, and other evill and unlawfull behaviours, done and committed, aſwell by the ſaid Merchants, as by their Servants and Factors, in cauſes of Merchandize. As alſo all others, not exerciſing the Trade of Merchandize; are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be dealt withall, by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as is contained in the reſtraints of the ſaid Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, of the moneth of May, hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpecified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, are
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121272:26"/> not to deal with the contracts of Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, either fained, or otherwiſe unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, whereby the offender, by all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable judgement deſerveth puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: As is contained in the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> all Civill cauſes, between men, of what quality ſoever, beſides thoſe which concern Trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, or matter of Exchange, be it by gift of the dead, by Will, or in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Marriage, enterchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of goods by conſent, and all other ſuch like Contracts: be all exempted from the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, As is contained in the ſaid reſtraints.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls are not to meddle with any oppoſition made againſt the execution of any of their Sentences, or ordinances; as is before expreſſed, and contained in the ſaid reſtraints.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121272:26"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The Authority of the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls, is onely in Civill cauſes, according as before is recited: and all ſuch forfeitures as ſhall happen, ſhall be arbitrated by the diſcretion of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and diſpoſed of, as before is ſaid.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> touching all matters that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Authority of the Prior and Conſuls, and do appertain to their knowledge, all other Judges, their Deputies, or Aſſignes, within all the Kings Dominions, cannot impeach or gainſay: neither ſhall they croſſe or contradict any thing, directly, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, whatſoever the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, or their Officers ſhall do: As is mentioned in the Letters Patents, in the Moneth of May.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121272:27"/>
                  <head>The matters wherein they may Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily proceede.</head>
                  <p>THe King in his ſaid Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the moneth of May, hath named and ſpecified the ſaid matters Summaries, the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof doth appertain to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, which be theſe: Acknowledgement of Bills, Reſcriptions, Letters of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, Letters of Advice, Receipts, Blanks ſigned, Suerties, Garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Conſignations of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, of what ſum ſoever: And all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther circumſtances, belonging and concerning the Trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, and matters of Exchange; As is more amply contained in the Letters Patents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:121272:27"/>
                  <head>The manner how to proceede in matters to be delivered upon a brief and ſummary triall, untill definitive ſentence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Kings Ordinance.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall cauſe all Plaintiffs at their firſt comming before them, in perſon, or by their Atturnies ſufficiently au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized, to nominate a place in the ſame Town, for his reſidence or abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and in default thereof, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall refuſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their demands, defences, and oppoſitions, ſpecially the Plaintiffs, as is contained in the firſt Article of the Kings Ordinance in the ſpeciall clauſe, That all Litigans, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, are at all times authorized, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in their ſaid Juriſdiction, ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the expedition of Suits, and <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121272:28"/> the eaſe of all Merchants trading in that place: except thoſe dayes, and holy dayes, in which the Court of Parliament of the ſaid place doth not ſit: according to which Order, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls may intermit the exerciſes of their Authority: And excepting furthermore, the day of the feaſt of the Kings (called Twelf-day) in which the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls are new choſen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, in the ſaid cauſes, cannot grant more then one delay, which is a ſufficient advantage for the party offending, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of <hi>May:</hi> And ſhall be hereafter declared.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> if any queſtion ſhall ariſe, for the acknowledgements of Bills, the party that is adjourned ſhall be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but one default, as above ſaid; to come, either to confeſſe, or deny
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121272:28"/> his deed: And having made one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, his Bill ſhall be held as confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and available, from the day that the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall give their Sentences: as is contained in the Kings Ordinances, and in the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, for the acknowledgement of Bills.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may take notice, that their Authority is greater in the acknowledgement of Bills, then the Authority of any other Judges, and more then the foreſaid Ordinance doth expreſſe: For the ſaid Ordinance doth extend but to the adjourning of the ſaid perſons onely. And the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, upon one onely default, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice left at the lodging of the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, may aver all Bills, and declare the ſame to be payable, As is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſaid Letters Patents, of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> all Debtors and Defendants, being in Queſtion for the ſayd <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121272:29"/> matters, Summary and Proviſionall, ſhall be by their Creditors and Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs onely once warned to appear; That is, at a competent day and hour, before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to accept or deny the demand, which ſhall be made againſt them by their Creditors and Plaintiffs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> all warnings or adjournments that ſhall be given at the firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of any Proces, ſhall contain ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily all the demands of the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe, to the end that the Defendant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adjourned, may come prepared for his anſwer, at the day and time aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: As is contained in the third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Kings Ordinances in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> of Adjournments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the Meſſenger or Serjeant, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the ſaid Prior and Conſuls Letters of Summons, touching the ſaid matter Summary, he muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ <pb n="57" facs="tcp:121272:29"/> the perſon himſelf, if he can finde him: otherwiſe, he ſhall fix, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the Coppie of the Demand, as his ſaid Warrant, at the door of the lodging of him that is ſummoned, and the ſame to be duly proved: and ſhall afterwards give knowledge unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences done therein: as is contained in the ſaid Letters Patents of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> foraſmuch as in the foreſaid matters, the Plaintiff, may (in regard of one default) obtain advantage in his cauſe, as is contained in the ſixth Article of the Kings Ordinances, in the
<hi>Rubrick</hi> of Serjeants: Therefore all executions, or Warrants of all Meſſengers or Serjeants, ſhall be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and ſigned by two Witneſſes, or of one at the leaſt: And the ſaid Meſſengers and Serjeants, ſhall be bound to leave a Coppy thereof, with the parties ſo aſſigned, or elſe to ſix the ſame upon the door of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121272:30"/> lodging, as beforeſaid, although they make reſiſtance; And to make men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Warrants they have ſerved at the charges of the Plaintiff, as is contained in the firſt and laſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Kings Ordinances in the Rubrick of Adjournments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the party ſo warned in, make not his appearance at the time to him aſſigned, then the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may proceed againſt him in the ſaid Cauſes, by ſeizing of his Goods, ſo far as the ſums ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount unto, pretended to be owing to the Plaintiff, or by arreſting and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning the party adjourned, if he may be taken, and ſo to detain him, untill he ſhall put into the hands of the Juſtice, the like ſums pretended to be owing to the Plaintiff: And this, in caſe where the party warned and impriſoned would declare nothing in his defence, againſt the other party: The Moneys firſt depoſited in the Court, as the Conſervator of the <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121272:30"/> Fairs of the ſaid City of <hi>Lion</hi> doth, and is contained in ſaid the Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>February</hi> hereafter expreſſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Without ſeizure of Goods, it is lawfull for the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, at the requeſt of the Plaintiff, to proceed againſt the Debtor by arreſt and impriſonment, if that be thought the eaſieſt way to do right to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, without exhibiting the Proceſſe: Like as the Conſervator of the ſaid City of <hi>Lion</hi> doth, according to the will and pleaſure of the late King <hi>Francis,</hi> contained in the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Pattents of the Moneth of
<hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the like ſums be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned by the Defendant, he being heard in his defences, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſed or condemned by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, with charges and fines, according as the Caſe <pb n="60" facs="tcp:121272:31"/> ſhall require, and quality of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And if the Defendant be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, for want of depoſiting the monies in the Court, according to the demand of the Plaintiffe, heard upon his defence: The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, ſhall proceed againſt all ſuch perſons, as aboveſaid: And like as the Conſervator of the Faires of the ſaid City of
<hi>Lyon</hi> doth; To avoyd long proceedings, conſidering the Parties be preſent: and being for matters touching Trade of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize and Bills of Exchange.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> if he that is Warned in, do not make his appearance according as he is Warned to do, and is no pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, then, after one default, the ſayd Prior and Conſuls may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, by ſeizing of his goods, ſo far as the ſums contained in the demand of the adverſe party do amount unto. And they may order to call the ſayd debtor, that at a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121272:31"/> certain day, hour, and place, he may come to ſee his Goods ſo ſeized to be publikely ſold, to the end that the Plaintiff may be ſatisfied with the Money proceeding thereof, according to reaſon, without any further delay, as is contained in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the Goods ſo taken and ſeized be unmoveable, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls having cauſed the Out-cries to be made, and preſent ſale thereof, they ſhall cauſe the ſaid Goods to be committed to a certain Commiſſioner, by the Meſſenger, or Serjeant, who did execute the ſaid Out-cries; And the party who is the purſuer, ſhall cauſe to be intimated and ſignified the ſaid Out-cries to all men to whom it ſhall concern, and to annex the intimation of their ſaid Out-cries, and the returns of the Warrants under the Counter-Seal of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, upon pain otherwiſe to be of no effect, as is <pb n="62" facs="tcp:121272:32"/> contained in the Kings Ordinances in the Rubrick of Out-cries and Sales, in the ſecond and fourth Articles.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The Notice and Out-cries being made according to the form uſually obſerved in the City of <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louze,</hi> the Sentence and Decree of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls being given, upon the Goods ſo ſold, ſhall be put into execution in the behalf of him that offereth moſt, and is laſt inhanſer of the price, as it is ordinarily done in the Juriſdictions of the other Judges of the ſaid place, according to the Tenour of the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of the Moneth of <hi>May;</hi> and as it is contained in the fifth Article of the Kings Ordinances in the Rubrick of Obligations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Foraſmuch as the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, by the Tenour of the ſaid Letters, may uſe the Rites and means in the exerciſing of their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121272:32"/> which other Judges of the Kingdom do uſe: The ſaid Prior and Conſuls may upon the interpoſition of Decree, obſerve and keep the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Judges of
<hi>Normandy,</hi> contained in the twenty fourth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Kings Ordinances, in the Rubrick of Abolitions, Confeſſions, and Grants,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereof the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour enſueth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Whereas the Returns of many Lands and Inheritances do paſſe by one onely Decree, upon any perſon for his debts, although there be many inhanſers of price, yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſhall ſuffer one onely Decree to paſſe, which ſhall be by the laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanſer, to whom the adjudication ſhall be made; And the Regiſter cannot conſtrain the other parties, ſpecially the party who obtained the Decree, to take the Letter of Decree and Eſtate; but they ſhall ſuffer the ſaid Inhanſers to take the Letters of their Inhanſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments onely; and the ſaid party who <pb n="64" facs="tcp:121272:33"/> obtained the Decree, to take the Act of that which ſhall be ordained upon his oppoſition, or elſe the ſaid Prior and Conſuls may make the Act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, to the other Judges, to whom the knowledge of the oppoſitions do concern.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>18.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> For all executions where there is a command to pay within a certain time, it ſhall not be needfull for the validity of the Warrant of the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries and Notice, or other ſeizing of Goods or perſon, to make farther en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of Goods moveable: But a command duly made by a Meſſenger or Serjeant to the perſon, or warning left at his Lodging, ſhall ſuffice. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which, the Goods ſeized, or the perſon arreſted, ſhall remain untill ſuch time as he hath obeyed the ſaid Command; as is contained in the Kings Ordinances in the eleventh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Clauſe of Obligations: And in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> or otherwiſe they <pb n="65" facs="tcp:121272:33"/> may proceed to the ſale of the Goods, as is before ſpecified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. 19.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the Goods ſo ſeized be moveables, then after one default, they ſhall be ſold publikely to him that offers moſt, to make ſatisfaction to the Plaintiff; And before the ſale of the ſaid Goods, the Plaintiff ſhall cauſe the Defendant to be warned to come ſee his Goods ſold and delivered to him that bids moſt, according to the cuſtome, and of the Judges of the ſaid place, as it is contained in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the ſaid parties warned do make their appearance at the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and do ſhew any thing againſt the demand of the Plaintiff, being by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls condemned to depoſite and conſign the ſums contained in the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, they cannot hinder the ſaid <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121272:34"/> depoſiting, although they do appeal from the ſaid ſentence which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſionall, and cannot be withſtood, or ſuſpended by appeal, as is contained in the laſt Article of the Kings Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and in the Clauſe of proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Sentences; and for want of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſiting and obeying the ſaid Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may conſtrain the Oppoſers, by arreſt, and by impriſonment of their perſons, as is contained in the two Letters Patents of the Moneths of <hi>May</hi> and <hi>February</hi> hereafter expreſſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If oppoſition be made againſt the ſeizing, ſale, or delivering of the Goods, or againſt the Out-cries or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſitions of Decree, or againſt any other chief point, where oppoſition may take place, the Money being duly depoſited in the Court, for the matter of the Authority of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, the parties ſo oppoſing themſelves, ſhall be ſent to their Judge and chief men of their Province, to <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121272:34"/> declare before them the cauſes of their oppoſitions, as is contained in certain Letters of the Kings, Given at
<hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Bleau,</hi> the ſeventh day of <hi>December,</hi> 1551. Read and publiſhed according to their Tenours in the Parliament of the ſaid City of <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> the ninth day of <hi>February</hi> in the ſame yeer.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>22.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the party warned do offer ſecurity, yet notwithſtanding he ſhall be cauſed to depoſite, and then have power to call his ſecurity, (the Money being depoſited in the Court) who being called before he be accepted for ſecurity, ſhall depoſite in the like manner, that after they may proceed as well againſt him, as againſt the principall debter, according to reaſon: And all Sentences and Judgements that ſhall be given againſt the ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhall be put in execution, to wit, againſt the principall debter, for the principall ſum: And againſt the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curities for the charges, dammages, and intereſt onely; as it is contained <pb n="68" facs="tcp:121272:35"/> in the twentieth Article of the Kings Ordinances, in the Clauſe of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>23.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> To call a Security before Conteſtation of the Cauſe, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls cannot grant but onely one default, unleſſe the firſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity will call a third man for Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to whom they may grant ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther onely default; as it is contained in the ſecond, third, and fourth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Kings Ordinances, in the ſaid Clauſe of delayes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>24.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> In the ſaid matters to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt Refractories, there is no need to give any delay, but after one default to proceed as aforeſaid; for one onely default in the ſaid mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, doth give great advantage to one of the parties; as it is contained in the firſt Article of the Kings Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in the Clauſe of Warnings:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121272:35"/> And all delayes are left by the King to the diſcretion of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to grant them according to the quality of the perſons, cauſes, and places, as other Judges do.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the Plaintiff doth Comence any ſuite by craft, and cauſeth any execution thereof againſt his adverſe party, or otherwiſe, if the Defendant uſeth any crafty helps, or unlawfull means, to defraud the Plaintiff, and not to ſatisfie him; The ſaid Prior and Conſuls may condemn the party of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, (for uſing the ſaid deceit, or unlawfull means) in a forfeiture, and the ſame to be diſpoſed of as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; as is contained in the tenth Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Kings Ordinances in the Clauſe of Obligations, and in the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Pattents of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:121272:36"/>
                  <head>A note of ſuch Matters wherein it is needfull to have inſtruction, and knowledge of the Cauſe.</head>
                  <p>ALL thoſe Matters are ſpecified and named particularly in the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> even as is likewiſe named, Obligations, Aſſociations, either ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or particular, Nominations of perſons, or of Goods, Aſſurances, Accounts, and Auditing thereof, the giving up of the Reſt left in the hands of the Accountant, ſatisfaction of the whole or of a part, Tranſports, Delegations, Novations of Debts, Partnerſhips, Bargains, and other Acts concerning the buſineſſe of the ſaid Exchange, and all thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Firſt, The Kings pleaſure is, by the Tenour of the ſaid Letters of the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> that the ſaid Prior
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121272:36"/> and Conſuls do proceed to Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the debates and differences moved, or to be moved, by reaſon of the ſaid matters, after two defaults, and that the parties warned twice, and making no appearance the ſecond day appointed them, ſhall undergo the ſame Judgement: Note that the King hath not limited any time for the ſaid defaults, but leaveth the ſame to the diſcretion of the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, who are to limit the ſame accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the diſtance of the place, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the party warned, commodity of the time, and cauſe of the buſineſſe, as all other Judges are accuſtomed to limit the defaults, according to the ſame circumſtances, and according to the common diſpoſition of right; And the tenour of the ſecond Article of the Kings Ordinances in the Clauſe of Delayes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Whether the parties warned do appear, or be abſent the day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them the ſecond time; The <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121272:37"/> ſaid Prior and Conſuls (before they do proceed to Judgement of the ſaid matters) ſhall hear the Plaintiffs, who upon their Oaths ſhall affirm their debts ſo demanded to be true, and contain nothing but truth: And then the defendants ſo warned being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, anſwering by credit, which is as much to ſay, that it is true, that the demand of the Plaintiff do contain truth: And forthwith, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls condemning them to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the ſaid Plaintiff with all coſts preſently taxed, without any form of Proceſſe, by the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, according to the Kings pleaſure contained in the ſaid Letters of the Moneth of
<hi>May.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the parties ſo warned ſhall anſwer by no credit, which is as much to ſay, That the demands of the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs are not true in all, or in part, they ſhall then affirm the ſame upon their Oaths, and ſubmit themſelves to prove the contrary, as it is contained
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121272:37"/> in the firſt Article of the Kings Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in the Clauſe of Anſwers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the parties ſo warned make no appearance (the two de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults being paſt) then ſhall the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff be bound to ſend unto the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant a Copy of his demand, with his oath, to the end, that he may either oppoſe the ſame, or approve it, which the Plaintiff may do either by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or by his Atturney, intimating unto him, That if he fails therein, that then the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, will proceed againſt him ſummarily to Judgement, upon the Plaintiffs concluſion, as it is ſaid before.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the parties do vary in their demands, they ſhall be bound to give in writing, both under their hands and oaths, thoſe points wherein they vary, and that within eight dayes, to the end that diligent enquiry may be made thereof; as it is contained in the <pb n="74" facs="tcp:121272:38"/> third Article of the Kings Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Clauſe of Articles agreed upon.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Inquiries.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, their Lieutenants and Deputies, in making their Inqueſt, may not admit of any witneſſes, nor take their oaths, nor proceed in proof, except the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe party be firſt called thereunto, or elſe their proceedings in ſuch a caſe ſhall be of no force; and if the party ſhall make default, after he hath been twice called, they may then admit of the Witneſſes, and proceed to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and all things thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing; as it is contained in the twelfth, thirteenth, and fourteenth Articles of the Kings Ordinances in the Clauſe of Commiſſaries to make Inqueſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:121272:38"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If inquiry be needfull to be made for both parties, and one of the parties will appeal from the Prior and Conſuls and from their Deputies, then the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and their Deputies, may make inquiry in the behalf of the party that doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal; as it is contained in the fifteenth Article of the foreſaid Clauſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The ſaid Prior and Conſuls, in making their inquires, can give but one onely default, within which time the parties muſt make report of their inquiries duly to be made, and ſealed up with their Seals; as is it contained in the ninth, tenth, and eleventh Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the Kings Ordinances in the Clauſe of Delayes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ART. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> Except the parties have uſed their diligence in making the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries within the time limited them,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121272:39"/> and cannot within that time finiſh the ſame, then upon due proof made of their diligence ſo uſed, in ſuch caſe the ſaid Prior and Conſuls may give them one onely delay more, after the which time they cannot make any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquiry, by witneſſes or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: as it is contained in the 12. and 13. Articles of the ſaid Ordinances.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the parties accepted of to make enquiry before the ſaid Prior and Conſulls, may uſe all ſorts of lawfull proofs, aſwell by right as by the Kings Ordinances; Provided that the ſame be done as breefely as can be, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the power of the Authority, of the ſaid Prior and Conſulls: All which is to be done in civill manner, be it by witneſſe, by writings, publike or private, by collection of Letters, by oath in the fulfilling of all proof: and otherwiſe, according as the caſe ſhall require, to know the truth, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Conſciences of the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="article">
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:121272:39"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> if in the end of the cauſe of Demands and Articles of the Parties, there be found any Article falſe and deceitfull, he that hath affirmed the ſame ſhall be amerced by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, an hundreth ſols, half thereof to the Kings uſe, and the other half to the parties: as it is contained in the 15. Article of the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Anſwers. And they may make uſe of the ſame penalties, againſt all parties, who ſhall not within eight dayes after all delayes, give in all their Demands and things contrary thereunto, being ſo ordered by the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls: as it is contained in the fourth Article of the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Articles of Agreement.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and their Deputies, in the proving of any matter in the behalf of any man
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121272:40"/> whatſoever, can take but ten witneſſes, and them ſecretly, the one after the other, upon an Arbitrary Amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein the ſaid Prior and Conſuls and their Deputies may be condemned by the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame place: And that all witneſſes whom they ſhall take here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in above the ſaid number, ſhall be rejected; as it is contained in the Title of Witneſſes, and likewiſe upon a matter in the Kings Ordinances.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> The inquiries being made, the Parties there, both or ſeverally, ſhall be bound to put in their excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or reproaches, within three dayes after the receiving the ſaid Inquiries, without any further delay, upon pain to be refuſed; as it is contained in the ſecond Article of the Kings Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Title of Reproaches.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Contradictions againſt the Letters and Exceptions, ſhall be <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121272:40"/> given in, within eight dayes after the ſaid Reproaches, and Exceptions, without any further delay, otherwiſe to be denied; as it is contained in the ſixth Article of the ſaid Ordinances.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> After publication made of the ſaid Inquiries, no Reproaches and Exceptions ſhall be permitted to be given in; but they ſhall proceed to Judgement, and to the deciding of the Cauſe, upon the former proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; as it is contained in the third Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the Kings Ordinances.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> All Inquiries, conſidering they cannot be other then Civill, ſhall for Actions of Caſe be publiſhed before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, having firſt obſerved the Tenour of the Articles here before immediately written; as it is contained in the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Inqueſts: and every party in the end of the Cauſe, may retire his <pb n="80" facs="tcp:121272:41"/> own, if he ſo pleaſe, as it is obſerved in the Juriſdiction of other inferiour Judges.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Production.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> If the proof be to be made by Writings, then the Parties are to bring in all the ſame Writings; by which they pretend to prove their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, within three dayes, without any further delay, unleſſe the diſtance of the place do require any more time; as it is contained in the third Article of the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Productions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> If the Parties produce any Writings that concern not the cauſe (to trouble the Judgement of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls) they may then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce the ſame party that ſhall bring in any ſuch Writings, in a hundred ſoles, ten ſhillings; as it is contained
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121272:41"/> in the ſecond Article of the foreſaid Title, to be imployed as it is ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid reſpite of three daies, or other reſpits, given by the diſcreet deliberation of the ſaid Prior and Conſulls, being paſt, the parties ſhall not after be permitted to produce any further Writings, but the proces ſhall be judged in the ſame ſtate, as it ſhall be found at the expiring of the reſpite, as it is contained in the fourth Article of the foreſaid Title of Productions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the Regiſter of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, ſhall be bound to keep a little Inventory of all the Writings that ſhall be produced, and ſhall cauſe the Parties that produce them, to write their names upon every one of them, to the end that none of the writings ſo produced, be altered or loſt, which might happen to be of great importance, ſpecially amongſt <pb n="82" facs="tcp:121272:42"/> Merchants, between whom often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times do ariſe differences of great ſums, conteined in little papers; As bils of Debts, and letters of Exchange: And likewiſe to the end that all Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſo produced, might be ſeen to agree with the tenour of the Invento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in the deciding of the Proces: as it is contained in the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Inventories.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>5</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Regiſter ſhall not take out any Coppy of matters of effect out of the ſaid Inventory, neither for the one party nor for the other, but onely in the cauſe, and for the end wherefore the ſaid writings are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, under the amercement of one hundred ſols, to be imployed to the profit of the ſaid Exchange, as the Atturnies of parties in other Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, are condemned in the like ſum, to be imployed to their Chappell: as it is contained in the ſecond Article of the ſaid Ordinances, in the Title of Productions.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:121272:42"/>
                  <head>Of Sentences.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt, the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, according to the certainty and truth of the proofs and allegations made before them by the parties, ſhall pronounce their Sentences cleerly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding the Proces, under pain of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment by the Court of Parliament of the ſaid place, upon the reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Sentences: as it is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſecond Article of the ſaid Ordinances, in the Title of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> when the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls have pronounced their Sentence without correcting, adding or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the fame, the ſaid Regiſter ſhall give a Coppy of the ſaid Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences to either of the ſaid Parties, being required thereunto, upon an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary penalty to be ſet upon him, and <pb n="84" facs="tcp:121272:43"/> to be held a falſe man if he doth the contrary; as it is contained in the third Article of the foreſaid Title.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the Kings pleaſure is, that all Sentences given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, both interlocutory and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitive, ſhall be of force and effect, even as thoſe of other Judges, as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the laſt Article of the ſaid Title of Sentences.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Arbitrators.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ITem,</hi> the Merchants of the juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the ſaid Exchange of <hi>Thoulouze,</hi> as well by their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, as by the command of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may refer their differences to Arbitrators, from whoſe ſentence, they may appeal to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, who as they ſhall ſee cauſe, may reform, or confirm the Sentence of the ſaid Arbitrators.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:121272:43"/>
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the appellation of the Sentence of the Arbitrators, ſhall not be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Arbitrement be performed, by the party that doth appeal; upon condition of reſtauration in the end of the Proces, if it be ſo thought good by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls: as it is contained in the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Arbitrators.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> the ſaid Prior and Conſuls are to note, that no Merchant, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being of their Juriſdiction, can tranſport, or make over their intereſt to any perſon Priviledged, and not ſubject to the ſame Juriſdiction, be it by gift, ſale, or Exchange, or by any other meanes, thereby to avoyd their Authority, or elſe the ſame tranſports or poſſeſſions, ſhall be of no effect, and the loſſe of their right and cauſe: as it is contained in the firſt and ſecond <pb n="86" facs="tcp:121272:44"/> Articles of the Kings Ordinances, in the Title of Ceſſions.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> all Scriveners, who ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any ſuch tranſports ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, in an arbitrary penalty: and further ſhall be condemned, to pay unto the adverſe Party, al his coſts and charges, which he hath ſuſtained by means thereof; as is contained in the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of the foreſaid Rubrick, taken of the common diſpoſition of the right.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Accuſations.</head>
                  <p>THe Parties may accuſe the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and others of their Juriſdictions, if they have law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſe ſo to do, And that not in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but by word, in his preſence whom they ſuſpect: And their accuſations ſhall be ſummarily examined and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided; and if in caſe the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhould be accuſed, then
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121272:44"/> the moſt ancient Merchants, and thoſe who have had the firſt pre-eminence in the ſaid Exchange, ſhall ſit in the place of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls: as is obſerved in the other Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and contained in the Kings Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, in the Title of Accuſations.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Diſtributions.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THe ſaid Prior and Conſuls, may diſtribute the Proces unto the moſt ancient Merchants, that be moſt expert in the matters that be in Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, to make a true report unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls: according to the allegations and proofs of the ſaid parties, to the end to decide the ſame, according to right; without any ſalle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to be given to the ſaid Merchants, in regard of their report.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> all Merchants to whom the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall diſtribute <pb n="88" facs="tcp:121272:45"/> the Proces, they ſhall be ſubject to take the advice of the Advocate, and Atturney of the ſaid Exchange, or of any others, if there be any difficulty in the cauſe, to the end to diſcern the right, and to make the better report thereof unto the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, that they may the ſooner end the ſame, according to reaſon and right, and at the charges of their parties purſuants, like as the Conſervator of the Faires of the ſaid city of
<hi>Lion</hi> doth.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Charges and Dammages.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="article">
                     <head>ARTICLE. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>FIrſt, all Charges and Damages ſhall be taxed by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls to a certain ſum, as it ſhall truly appear unto them, by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Proces, having a regard to the quality of the Parties, and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the cauſes, without receiving from the Parties any declaration of their charges, and without any other <pb n="89" facs="tcp:121272:45"/> order of proceeding, as is contained in the laſt Article of the Kings Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the Rubrick of Charges: like as the Conſervator of the Faires of the ſaid <hi>Lion</hi> doth; and is contained in the Letters Patents of the moneth of <hi>February,</hi> hereafter ſpecified.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="article">
                     <head>ARTIC. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> if for the repair of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Damages, and Intereſt, any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were condemned in a penalty, and to remain in priſon untill he had ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the ſame, by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, the ſaid party cannot be by them inlarged, without the expreſſe conſent of the Party intereſſed, or that he have ſatisfied him; As is contained in the ſeventh and eight Articles, in the Rubrick of Charges, and in the ſixt Article of the Rubrick of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="penalties" type="edict">
                  <head>Of Penalties.</head>
                  <p>ALL Penalties adjudged by the ſayd Prior and Conſuls (to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121272:46"/> imployed as before ſaid) ſhall be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied without delay, as is contained in the ſecond Article of the foreſaid Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Penalties.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="enabling_documents">
               <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
                  <div type="body_of_excerpt">
                     <head>An Extract out of the Regiſter of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</head>
                     <p>THe Court did peruſe King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Letters Patents in form of a Charter, and Ordinance, given at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> in the moneth of
<hi>March,</hi> 1566. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/> containing the ordaining, erecting and eſtabliſhing of a Common place in the City of <hi>Roan</hi> for Merchants, that they and their Factors may aſſemble themſelves there twice a day, at the uſuall houres, to traffick, and tranſact their buſineſſes, as they do in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change at <hi>Lions,</hi> and in the Burſe at
<hi>Tholouze:</hi> and alſo to meet and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelves every year in the ſaid common place: and to chooſe one Prior, and two Conſuls out of the Merchants, from year to year, to take <pb n="91" facs="tcp:121272:46"/> notice and Judge of ſuch things as are mentioned in the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; together with the Priviledges and Liberties contained at large there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. A Petition being preſented by the Citizens, Merchants, dwellers, and Inhabitants in this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> in the behalf of themſelves, and other Merchants reſorting and trafficking thither, concerning matters of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize; for the approving of which Grant, and for publiſhing of the ſaid Letters Pattents; It is ordered, that without any prejudice of the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons made againſt the publiſhing of the ſaid Letters Pattents and Charter, they ſhall be read, publiſhed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred. The Merchants that ſhall be choſen (according to the tenour thereof) to be the Prior, Conſuls, and Clerks of their Court, muſt be free Denizens, or elſe Naturalized, and married in this Country. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Election ſhall be made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Committee of two Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, named and deputed by the Court of Parliament for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <pb n="92" facs="tcp:121272:47"/> before which Committee the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and the Clerk of their Court ſhall take the oath requiſite for exerciſing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging their duties in their Offices and places.</p>
                     <p>The Regiſter of the ſaid Court of Conſuls, and the Clerk of the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance Office, muſt be inhabitants in the City of
<hi>Roan,</hi> in ſome publike and eminent place, which ſhall be choſen and aſſigned for that purpoſe.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in the Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 20 <hi>of</hi> July 1563.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>ſigned by</hi> De Goiſmare.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="endorsement">
                     <p>I <hi>Lewis Marc</hi> Purſuivant in the ſaid Court of Parliament, did afterwards read and publiſh the things above mentioned and contained, at the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the wayes, and in the publike places where Proclamations uſe to be read in this City of <hi>Roan;</hi> having firſt of all cauſed the Trumpet to be ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and Out-cries to be made after the uſuall manner, on Friday the <pb n="93" facs="tcp:121272:47"/> laſt day but one of
<hi>July,</hi> 1563. In witneſſe whereof I have hereunto ſet my hand and ſubſignature</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Lewis Marc.</signed> 
                     </closer>
                     <postscript>
                        <p>In the preſence of <hi>Peter Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taille</hi> the Trumpeter, and of many others there preſent at that time.</p>
                     </postscript>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="letters_patent">
                  <head>The Kings Letters Pattents, by which all Meſſengers of the Parliament, and all other, or any of the Sergeants of other Courts are enjoyned to put in Execution the Commands and Sentences given by the ſaid Priors and Conſuls: and to ſerve the Warrants, whenſoever they ſhall be required.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>CHarles</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c.</signed> 
                     <salute>To all our Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and Sergeants whom it ſhall concern, Greeting.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Whereas the late deceaſed King <hi>Henry</hi> our moſt honoured Lord and Father, hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and eſtabliſhed, in our City of
<hi>Roan</hi> one Prior, and two Conſuls, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="94" facs="tcp:121272:48"/> the manner uſed and obſerved at the Exchange in <hi>Lions,</hi> and at the Burſe in <hi>Tholouze.</hi> Which thing was approved of by our Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> after many and long ſuits: and yet, notwithſtanding, the moſt part of you do refuſe to put in execution ſentences given, and orders made by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, under colour and pretence, that our Bailiffs, Sheriffs, Admirals, the Maſters of our Waters and Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, and the reſt of our Judges or their Lieutenants, have inhibited you to warn any perſons before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, under great pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties, and amercements; ſo that by theſe means, the Edict of their eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing is made deluſory, voyd, and of no effect for them; although we are cheefly intereſſed in the buſineſſe, our intent being to make traffique to be uſed honeſtly in our Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are therefore to command and charge you, and every one of you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto required, to put in full and entire execution, all Ordinances, <pb n="95" facs="tcp:121272:48"/> Sentences, and Judgements given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and alſo to ſerve their Warrants, and Writs, and make returns thereof, as you, and every of you ſhall be required, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out asking any leave, <hi>Placet, Viſa,</hi> or <hi>Pareatis;</hi> neither ſhall any one of our Judges whatſoever, have power or authority to hinder you, or to call you into any of their Courts, or Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for we have expreſly interdicted and forbidden, and do interdict and forbid them by theſe preſents, ſo to do, under the penalty of anſwering in their own particular perſons, for all charges, dammages, and intereſts of the parties; for ſuch is our pleaſure, notwithſtanding any Edicts, Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Reſtraints, Commands, Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitions, and Letters whatſoever to the contrary.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at</hi> Paris
<date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 23. day of <hi>October</hi> in the year of our Lord 1563. <hi>and of our reign the third.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed by the King in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <pb n="96" facs="tcp:121272:49"/>
                        <hi>Morin</hi> with his Subſignature, and ſealed with one onely labell of the great Seal, with yellow wax.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <argument>
                     <p>The ſaid Patents ſignified unto the Bailiff, Sheriff, the water Sheriffe, Admiralty and Sergeants, by <hi>Cireule</hi> the Meſſenger, according to the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the 15. of <hi>November</hi> 1563. and the 3. of
<hi>September</hi> 1514.</p>
                  </argument>
               </div>
               <div type="letters_patent">
                  <div type="body_of_letters_patent">
                     <head>The Kings Letter Pattens in form of a Declaration, given upon the eſtabliſhing of the Judges Conſuls at Paris.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>CHarls</hi> by the Grace of God,</signed>
                        <salute>to all unto which theſe preſents ſhall come, Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>We give you to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that upon the Petition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto us in our Councell by the Merchants of our City of
<hi>Roan;</hi> We have through the advice of the ſaid Councell, declared and ordered and do declare and order by theſe preſents, That the Edict and order made by us at <hi>Paris</hi> in the moneth of <pb n="97" facs="tcp:121272:49"/>
                        <hi>November,</hi> in the yeer 1563. for the eſtabliſhing in our ſaid City of <hi>Paris,</hi> one Judge, and four Conſuls of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, with a Juriſdiction and Power of taking notice of all Proceſſes and differences between Merchants, in matters of Merchandice; ſhall have place, and ſhall be kept and obſerved henceforward, as well for what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth the manner of the Election, as for the Juriſdiction of the Prior and Conſuls of Merchants heretofore eſtabliſhed in our ſaid Citie of <hi>Roan:</hi> To exerciſe and to execute Juſtice henceforward, by them that ſhall be choſen from yeer to yeer, between Merchants, in matters of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice onely, according to the Tenour of the ſaid Declaration. And the Counſellours of the common Citie-Hall (except they be of the number of them that are choſen) ſhall have no authority to intermeddle with their affairs during the times of free Fayrs, as they do pretend to belong unto them by the Charter of the deceaſed King <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh, given at <hi>Arras</hi> 
                        <pb n="98" facs="tcp:121272:50"/> in the moneth of <hi>May,</hi> 1417. which we have called in, upon that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and in ſo doing, have united, and do by theſe Preſents unite the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Juriſdiction of the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours of the Common-Hall, to that of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, and upon the Remonſtrance alſo made by the ſaid Merchants: That ordinary Judges do ſtill take notice of the oppoſitions made againſt the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Sentences and Judgements given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, they pretending to know, and that they ought to take notice of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between Merchants, Drapers, Hoſiers, Shoe-makers, Mercers, Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, and others, that ſell and buy by Retail; ſaying, That it is a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe belonging to the Bailiffs Court of the Citie, and to the Lieutenants, and to the Sheriffs. We, to make an end of thoſe difficulties and hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the execution of our Edicts, have declared and ordered, and do declare and order, and it is our Will and Pleaſure, That the taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice <pb n="99" facs="tcp:121272:50"/> of all oppoſitions which ſhall happen hereafter againſt the execution of the Sentences and Judgements gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Prior and Conſuls of the Merchants of <hi>Roan,</hi> and of all diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in matters of Merchandice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Merchants onely, either ſellers or buyers, by the Great, or by Retail; ſhall remain, and belong to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, privatively from any other Judges, as wel ordinury, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate, Deputies, Inferiour, as of Our ſaid Court of Parliament at <hi>Roan:</hi> Forbidding them the taking of the ſame in the firſt Inſtance, being reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the parties to provide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by Appeal, in the caſes of Our Ordinance, and not otherwiſe.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, We do command Our truſtie and welbeloved, keeping Our ſaid Court of Parliament at <hi>Roan,</hi> to cauſe theſe Preſents to be read, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and regiſtred with an Extract ſigned, out of the Regiſter of Our Court of Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> of the ſaid Ordinances given at <hi>Paris</hi> in the moneth of <hi>November,</hi> 1563. to keep <pb n="100" facs="tcp:121272:51"/> and obſerve the Contents thereof, and to cauſe them to be kept and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed inviolably, and in every point, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Form and Tenour thereof; cauſing all hinderances to the contrary to ceaſe, conſidering the good, and profit, and eaſe which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulteth from thence unto Merchants; and for the maintaining of Traffick, Negotiation, and otherwiſe. For, ſuch is Our Pleaſure, all pretended Priviledges, Statutes, Ordinances, or any other Letters to the contrary thereunto notwithſtanding.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Montpellier
<date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 29 <hi>of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1564. <hi>and in the fourth yeer of Our reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="endorsements">
                     <p>And upon the back-ſide it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſed,
<hi>By the King in his Councell, ſigned by</hi> Cauvet <hi>his Subſignature, with an appearance that the ſaid Letters were ſealed with a double Label.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreover, it is endorſed,
<hi>Read, publiſhed and regiſtred, with <pb n="101" facs="tcp:121272:51"/> the Extract of the Decree of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at</hi> Paris <hi>therein mentioned, at the requeſt of the Prior and Conſuls, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed for the Merchants in the Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> and alſo at the requeſt of the ſaid Merchants; with the conſent of the Kings Atturneys Generall, under the Clauſes contained in the Decree there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ordered, given, and now publiſhed.</hi> 1566.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>At</hi> Roan, <hi>in the Parliament.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed,</hi> Du Val his Subſignature.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="decree">
                  <head>Decrees, Ordinances and Preſidents of the Court of Parliament, given between the Bailiffs, Aldermen, Sheriffs of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> the Water-Sheriff, and the fourty Sergeants of the ſaid City, of the one part: And the Priour and Conſul Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the ſaid Common Place, of the other part: Upon the approving of the Kings Letters-Patents given at
<hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellier</hi> the <hi>29</hi> of December, <hi>1564.</hi> above inſerted. On the <hi>13</hi> of July, <hi>1565.</hi> at <hi>Roan,</hi> in the Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:121272:52"/>BEtween the Prior and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls eſtabliſhed for Merchants in this Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> and the Merchants, dwellers and inhabitants of the ſaid Citie, Plaintiffs, deſiring the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Grant, and publiſhing of certain Letters Patents of the Kings Declaration, containing an Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Juriſdiction; M.
<hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Rome</hi> Lord of <hi>Freſquiennes,</hi> now Prior; <hi>Peter Dumoncel</hi> and <hi>Allonce le Seigneur,</hi> the Conſuls, being preſent: and by M. <hi>Richard le fae</hi> their Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, on the one part: And the Bailiff and Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> the Water-She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff, and the Counſellours of the Common-Hall of the ſaid Citie, and the fourty Sergeants of the ſaid place, Defendatns againſt the ſaid approving of the Grant, and publiſhing of the ſaid Letters Patents; appearing by M. <hi>Martin le Roy, James de Verdun,</hi> and <hi>Peter Deffaies,</hi> their Atturneys, of the other part, in the preſence of the Kings Atturney Generall. The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being heard, and the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney <pb n="103" facs="tcp:121272:52"/> in a verball Plea; and that <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got</hi> for the ſaid Attorney Generall, ſaid, That the cauſe of the Order which was made, that the ſaid Letters Patents ſhould be communicated unto the Defendants, was, to hear if they could alleadge any thing for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good and utility, which the Court and the Kings Officers intended onely to regard. And having heard what is pleaded, the ſaid Atturney Generall ſhall give his Concluſions in writing: that all being ſeen and peruſed by the Court, they may do juſtice therein. The Court hath ordered, and doth now order, That the ſaid Atturney Generall ſhall give his Concluſions in writing, upon the approving and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the ſaid Letters-Patents, as was intended at the Councell. The cauſe pleaded by the Defendants, was annexed thereunto.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given as above: the Copie being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined with the Original.</dateline>
                     <signed>Signed, <hi>de Boiſleueſque,</hi> with his Subſignature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dispute">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:121272:53"/>
                  <head>The eleventh day of December <hi>1655.</hi> in the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>BEtween maſter <hi>William Puchot</hi> the Sheriff of
<hi>Roan,</hi> plaintiff, deſiring the grant of a certain Requeſt preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him unto the Court: whereby the Letters Patents of the Kings De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, obtained by him at <hi>Rochel</hi> the 15 of <hi>September</hi> laſt paſt, might be read, publiſhed, and regiſtred; the Contents whereof to be enjoyed, and uſe made of by the ſaid Sheriff, being then preſent himſelf in perſon, and by Maſter <hi>William de Bourgongne</hi> his Atturny, of the one part; and the Prior and Conſuls eſtabliſhed by the Merchants of this City of <hi>Roan</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, and oppoſing themſelves againſt the grant of the ſaid requeſt: <hi>Bardin Bignon,</hi> the Warden of the common Burſe of the Merchants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent: and by Maſter <hi>Richard le Fae</hi> their Atturney, of the other part: in the preſence of the Kings Atturney <pb n="105" facs="tcp:121272:53"/> Generall: when <hi>Ange</hi> had ſaid in the behalf of the ſaid <hi>Puchot</hi> the Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> that he had formerly made an oppoſition unto the publiſhing, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and grant ſued, and deſired in the ſaid Court, by the Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, of certain Letters Pattents, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the King at their ſuite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, pretending to encreaſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large by them their juriſdiction. And though they were eſtabliſhed and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to take onely notice of traffick, and Merchandiſe between Merchant and Merchant: Yet they endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to procure and obtain that it might be granted unto them to take notice of proceſſes and differences, which might ariſe and happen out of things ſold by retaile for the ordinary uſes, and for the neceſſities of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and of the Kings Subjects, to the great prejudice of the ſaid Sheriffs Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction. Upon which oppoſition, and other contradiction made againſt the publiſhing deſired by the ſaid Priour, and Conſuls of their ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters given at <hi>Montpellier</hi> the 29. of <hi>December,</hi> 1564.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:121272:54"/>The caſe was laid all open plainly, and given his Majeſty to underſtand in his Privie Councell, where he was preſent, that by the Contents of the ſaid Letters Pattents of the 29 of
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1563. ſo obtained in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the ſaid Conſuls, they could not extend them to the taking notice of ſuch Proceſſes as ſhould ariſe by reaſon of that which is ſold by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile for the uſe and ordinary neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the people: and nevertheleſſe the King, to make the buſineſſe more cleer, had moreover by the ſaid let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, being a decree of his Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, of the 15. of <hi>September,</hi> declared and ordered, That by the ſaid Letters Pattents of the 29. of <hi>December</hi>
1564. his Majeſties intent was, that the ſaid Priour and Conſuls ſhould know of no other differences ſoever, but in matters of traffique negotiation, and Merchandiſe between Merchants one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, according to the tenour of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, and Letters Patents of their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining and eſtabliſhing, and that they ſhould have no authority to take <pb n="107" facs="tcp:121272:54"/> any notice of thoſe differences that might ariſe for any Merchandize ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſold or bought for the ordinary neceſſities or uſe of the Kings Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: which notice his Majeſties will and intent was, and now is, that it ſhould belong and remain with the ſaid Sheriffs of <hi>Roan,</hi> and with other ordinary Judges, though the buyers, and ſellers be Merchants, ſince this kinde of ſelling and buying is not made by way of Merchandiſe, but onely for their neceſſity and uſes, the ſaid <hi>Ango</hi> concluding in the behalf of the ſaid Sheriff of <hi>Roan</hi> to the ends of his requeſt, and that thereby the Letters Pattents of the Kings Decla-Declaration of the 15. of
<hi>September,</hi> now read, publiſhed, and regiſtred, the Contents whereof to be enjoyed and uſe made of by the ſaid Sheriff according to the form and tenour of the ſame, and that inhibition may be made unto the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, for attempting any thing to the prejudice of them, deſiring charges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them in caſe of contradicting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:121272:55"/>Unto which <hi>Cadyot,</hi> for the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, Conſuls, and Merchants, hath ſaid that the ſaid Letters Pattents of the Declaration obtained by them, were communicated by Order of the Court to the Citizens Councellours of the Common hall of this City of
<hi>Roan,</hi> which have them ſtill in their hands; upon the reading and publiſhing whereof, the ſaid Sheriffs of <hi>Roan</hi> had oppoſed himſelf, as alſo the Bailiff of <hi>Roan</hi> and others. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the caſe was appointed in the Councell: the ſaid Sheriffe not ſignifying it unto the King, had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the ſaid Letters Patents of the Declaration, by which there might be done a formall prejudice unto the ſaid inſtance, which would have been judged nothing, (being ſeen, and the party not being heard) by the ſaid Letters Patents, an unuſuall thing and altogether unreaſonable; declaring, that he oppoſeth himſelf againſt it, and hindreth the ends of the ſaid Sheriffe of <hi>Roan</hi> his requeſt: maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that the ſaid Letters of the new <pb n="109" facs="tcp:121272:55"/> Declaration obtained by the ſame Sheriff, may not, nor muſt not be publiſhed nor take any effect to the prejudice of the ſaid inſtance appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Councell, which muſt be firſt decided: or elſe he maintaineth that firſt and before they can proceed farther in this buſineſſe, the parties muſt be ſent back to provide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves before the King, and that he hath many great and important rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to ſhew of which he is not at all inſtructed at the preſent, which to bring in he maintaineth howſoever that a competent time and delay muſt be given him, which delay hath been contradicted and hindred by the ſaid <hi>Ango,</hi> for the ſaid Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> conſidering the preceding delayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by him quoted, prefixed, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to come to make inhibition againſt his ſaid requeſt; when alſo <hi>Bigot</hi> had ſaid for the Kings Atturney Generall that the ſaid Lord our Soveraign by his laſt Letters of Declaration had made a very reaſonable limitation to <pb n="110" facs="tcp:121272:56"/> thoſe whom the Prior and Conſuls had obtained to enlarge the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction given unto them, by their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining and eſtabliſhing; deſiring that <hi>Cadyot</hi> Advocate for the ſaid Prior and Conſuls would ſay what he ſhould think good, if he did intend to ſay any thing elſe, or otherwiſe, that default might be given againſt him in his own preſence. The ſaid <hi>Cadyot,</hi> for the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his plea, and in deſiring that the parties might be ſent back to the King and to his Privy Councell, where they do intend to ſhew fully the conſequence and importance of the ſaid Letters of Declaration ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the ſame Sheriff of <hi>Roan;</hi> and in caſe they ſhould take effect, and the taking notice of what is ſold by retaile, ſhould be taken away from the ſaid Prior and Conſuls: the grant of Juriſdiction made unto them, would be ſo weakned, that the traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique of merchandize would be much retarded thereby, by the long ſuits againſt the Kings mind, and other <pb n="111" facs="tcp:121272:56"/> great and pertinent reaſons, which the ſaid Prior, Conſuls, and Merchants do intend to ſhew plainly.</p>
                  <p>The Court hath appointed and doth appoint the parties to the Councell upon the publiſhing, deſired upon the Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> of the Letters of the Kings Declaration of the 15. of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> to do right therein, in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inſtance alſo appointed to the ſaid Councell, by a decree of the 13. day of <hi>July</hi> laſt paſt, as it ſhall be found requiſite: in the mean time the ſaid Court hath made, and doth make inhibitions, and forbiddeth the ſaid Prior and Conſuls upon ſuch penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as belong to the caſe, to aſſume unto themſelves the taking notice of Proceſſes and differences ariſing out of Merchandiſes ſold, or bought for the ordinary neceſſities, or uſes of his Majeſties people and ſubjects, permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them onely to take notice of thoſe differences, that proceede by reaſon of traffique, and negotiation of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, between Merchants, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Ordinance and Letters
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121272:57"/> Pattents of his Majeſty, concerning their Ordaining and eſtabliſhing.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given as above,</dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed,</hi> Dudere, <hi>with his Subſignature.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>An extract out of the Regiſter of the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>THere was ſeen by the Court the Kings Letters-Patents given at
<hi>Montpellier</hi> the 29 day of <hi>December,</hi> 1564. ſigned by the King in his Councell <hi>Camus,</hi> and ſealed upon a double Label of yellow Wax, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Declaration, Order and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of the Juriſdiction of the Prior and Conſuls eſtabliſhed for the Merchants in this citie of
<hi>Roan;</hi> a Decree of the Court of Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> of the 18 day of <hi>January,</hi> 1563. upon the publiſhing of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and eſtabliſhing of a Judge and Conſuls in the ſaid citie of
<hi>Paris.</hi> There was ſeen alſo the ſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance tranſcribed, and inſerted into it: the Decree given between the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121272:57"/> and Conſuls, and the Bailiff and Sheriff of
<hi>Roan,</hi> the Water-Sheriff, the fourty Sergeants, and the Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of the common Hall of this ſaid citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> and the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney Generall, the 13 of <hi>July,</hi> 1565. An Act of the 14 of
<hi>April</hi> laſt, made afore the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Declaration made by them, that they intended no ways to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the franchiſes and liberties of Faires of this ſaid City of <hi>Roan,</hi> by the ſaid Pattents, and other Papers produced in the ſaid Court, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaid Ordinance of the 13. of <hi>July,</hi> 1565. a concluſion given in writing by the ſaid Atturney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, of the 13. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the ſaid year 1565. The Lawyers of the Bai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs, Sheriffs, of
<hi>Roan,</hi> Water-ſheriffs, and of the Counſellours of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon hall of this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> being all conſidered. It is ſaid that the Court conſidering the requeſt of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, immediately after the publiſhing of the firſt Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance made upon their ordaining and <pb n="114" facs="tcp:121272:58"/> eſtabliſhing, and with the conſent of the Kings Atturney Generall, hath ordered, and doth order, that the ſaid Letters Pattents with the extract of the decree of the Court of Parliament at
<hi>Paris,</hi> and the Declaration inſerted and tranſcribed therein, ſhall be read, publiſhed, and regiſtred in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſaid Court, upon the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and provided nevertheleſſe, that the Priors and Conſuls, which are now, and which ſhall be hereafter choſen, ſhall be bound to appear in the ſaid Bailiffs Court at <hi>Roan</hi> every year, on the uſuall dayes, and there to take their oathes as other Judges, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting unto the ſaid Court and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending thereon; end that the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall be made in the preſence of the two Preſidents, and Councellours of the ſaid Court, as before, according to the Decree given in that Court, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the approving and publiſhing of the firſt Ordinance of the ordaining and eſtabliſhing of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls; upon condition like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <pb n="115" facs="tcp:121272:58"/> that they ſhall Judge according as it is preſcribed by the Kings Laws and Ordinances, as well concerning unlawfull contracts, as concerning the number and quality of their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, which they ſhall call in (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a fit and competent number) to Judge: and alſo that they may not know, judge and decide caſes, finally and without appeal, but onely in ſuch caſes and no further than the Preſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Judges.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in the Parliament</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of</hi> Auguſt: the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſitting, 1556.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed</hi> Du Val, <hi>with a Subſignature.</hi>
                     </signed> 
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>The coppy being examined with the Originall.</p>
                  </postscript>
               </div>
               <div n="25 July 1566" type="certificate">
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>The</hi> 25. <hi>day of</hi> July,
1566.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Claudius Moyſi</hi> Purſuivant in his Majeſties Court of Parliament of <hi>Roan,</hi> do certifie that at the requeſt of the honourable <hi>Ferdinando de Quinta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoines</hi> Prior, <hi>Thomas du Pont,</hi> and <pb n="116" facs="tcp:121272:59"/> 
                     <hi>John Tanquart</hi> Conſuls of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of this ſaid City in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent year; have Signified the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the ſaid Court, dated the 30. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1566. unto <hi>Lewis Combaut, John Baudovin, Roger Bechin,</hi> and <hi>Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebert Marſellet,</hi> his Majeſties Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeants of this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> and the chief of every decury, ſpeaking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in perſons, and at their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes, for them, and all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Sergeants of their reſpective decuries in this ſaid City, that they nor any of them may not plead that they were ignorant thereof, or attempt any thing to the prejudice of the ſame, upon the penalties thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſommoning the ſaid chief per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of every decuries, to give ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all notice of it to the Sergeants of their decuries: to which end, I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto every one of the ſaid four chief perſons of the decuries, a coppy of the ſaid decree with a relation and return thereof, at the charges of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls.</p>
                  <p>Done by me the above ſaid Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuivant, <pb n="117" facs="tcp:121272:59"/> in the preſence of <hi>Peter du Val,</hi> and of <hi>Romain de Boſc,</hi> witneſſes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed</hi> Moiſi <hi>with his Subſignature.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letters_patent">
                  <head>The Kings Letters Pattents in manner of a Declaration given at <hi>Moulins,</hi> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the confirmation of the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Declarations heretofore granted to the Prior and Conſuls of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in
<hi>Roan,</hi> with an enlargement of their Juriſdiction, Regiſtring, and Decree of the approving thereof, and a Verball proceſſe of the reading of the ſame, made in the Bailywick, and in the Sheriffs Court of
<hi>Roan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div type="body_of_letters_patent">
                     <opener>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>CHarles</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <salute>to our truſty well beloved, keeping our Court of Parliament at <hi>Roan,</hi> Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>The Prior and Conſuls of the Merchants of our City of <hi>Roan</hi> have cauſed to be told and Remonſtranced unto us in our Privie Councell, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by our Edicts, Ordinances, and Declarations, given by us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <pb n="118" facs="tcp:121272:60"/> the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls: it is expreſly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited unto Judges in Ordinary, to aſſume unto themſelves the taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and Judging of ſuch caſes, which are attributed unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls. Yet notwithſtanding, they do commonly aſſume unto themſelves the taking notice, and judging of the ſaid matters between Merchants, and in matters of Merchandize, ſold or bought, either by whole ſale or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile: even ſo far, as to prohibite the parties to proceede any where elſe, but before them; and they do alſo forbid the Serjeants to execute the Sentences and commands of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, or to cite and warn any body before them, amercing them; ſo that the ſaid Serjeants make a ſcruple, and refuſe to aſſiſt and to be preſent in the ſaid Court of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls, as they are enjoyned by our Edicts and Declarations, which would be made by theſe means deluſory unto them, except we were pleaſed to provide for them in this
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121272:60"/> caſe, being therefore willing that for theſe cauſes, our Ordinances and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations may take place and effect, We charge you, and through the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our Councell, do expreſly command you by theſe preſents, that according unto our ſaid Ordinances and Declarations, you do expreſly prohibite the Judges in Ordinary, the Officers of our ſaid city of <hi>Roan,</hi> and others, whom it ſhall concern, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume unto themſelves the taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of matters granted by our ſaid Ordinances and Declarations unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, directly or indirectly, although the parties them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were willing to proceed afore afore them, and alſo to forbid the Advocates and Sollicitors to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the ſaid cauſes, nor to plead them before the Judges in Ordinary, upon the penalty of making voyd the ſuite, and of Arbitrary amercements, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, dammages, and intereſts of the parties, as well of the ſaid Judges, as againſt the Lawyers and Attornies: enjoyning all our Serjegants every one
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:121272:61"/> of them in their turns to aſſiſt and to be preſent at the dayes and houres in which the Court of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls uſeth to be kept; there to command ſilence, to put in ure and execution their Orders and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and to ſummon all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before them, and to ſerve their Warrants as they ſhall be required thereunto, and to give them ſuch ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reverence, as they owe unto Magiſtrates, conſtraining them and evey one of them ſo to do; and to ſuffer and obey by all due and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable meanes, and by impriſonment of their perſons. All oppoſitions and appeals to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, by reaſon of which we will not have any delay to be made, enjoyning likewiſe our Atturnies in every one of the ſeverall Courts, upon the duty of of their Office, to be aiding and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the execution of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and Authority of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents, which we will have to be read and publiſhed as well in our ſaid Court, as in every of the ſaid Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, <pb n="121" facs="tcp:121272:61"/> that none may pleade that they were ignorant thereof: for ſuch is our pleaſure.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Moulins
<date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 22. <hi>day of February</hi> 1566. <hi>and in the ſixth year of our Reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed by the King in his Councell.</signed>
                        <signed>Camus <hi>with his ſubſignature, and Sealed upon one Labell with the great Seal of yellow wax, and in the Margent of the ſaid letters Pattents it is written underneath.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="endorsement">
                     <p>Read, Publiſhed and Regiſtred, in the hearing of the Kings Atturney Generall, that they that have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them may enjoy them, as it is contained in the Ordinance given this day upon the publiſhing thereof at
<hi>Roan</hi> in the Parliament the 22. day of <hi>March,</hi> in the year mentioned in the Originall.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed</hi> De Boiſleueſque <hi>with his Subſignature.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <div type="body_of_document">
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:121272:62"/>
                     <head>Of the <hi>22</hi> of <hi>March, 1555.</hi> at
<hi>Roan</hi> in the Court of Parliament.</head>
                     <p>VPon the requeſt made verbally in the Court by <hi>de Bretignieres,</hi> Advocate, in the behalf of the Prior and Conſuls eſtabliſhed for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants in this Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> which have obtained ſome certain Letters-Patents of the Kings Declaration, for the ordering of their Juriſdiction, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at <hi>Moulins</hi> the 22 of
<hi>February</hi> laſt paſt, appearing by M. <hi>Richard le Fac</hi> their Atturney; that it may pleaſe the Court, in approving the ſaid Letters-Patents, to cauſe them to be read, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and regiſtred, that the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls may enjoy them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the form and tenour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: <hi>Bigot</hi> did afterwards declare, by the Atturney-Generall, that he would not hinder it, in caſe there was no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating from the Ordinances made by the Court, as well upon the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Ordinance for the ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <pb n="123" facs="tcp:121272:62"/> of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, as from others; even from that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which was given upon the 11 day of <hi>December</hi> laſt, between the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff of
<hi>Roan,</hi> and them: by which it was ordered, that the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhould not take notice of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences ariſing about things ſold for common neceſſities; but onely of ſuch as did ariſe concerning Traffick between Merchant and Merchant: without any prejudice likewiſe to the Court which uſeth to be kept in the common-Hall of this citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> during the Fayrs: and by the Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made between them and the Citizens counſellours of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Hall, that the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of the Merchants ſhould have no power, nor no authority of aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling themſelves in the ſaid common-Hall, for the giving and allowing of charges.</p>
                     <p>Becauſe alſo they may neither there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by aſſume unto themſelves any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over Judges in ordinary, to puniſh them, pretending that they have uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped <pb n="124" facs="tcp:121272:63"/> upon their Juriſdiction. And <hi>Ango</hi> for the Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> and
<hi>Ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi> in the behalf of the Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of the ſaid Common-Hall, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing by M. <hi>Peter de Hays</hi> and <hi>Marten le Roy,</hi> their Atturneys reſpectively; have declared, that except the ſaid Prior and Conſuls would give their aſſent unto the ſaid Qualification and Reſtraints mentioned by his Majeſties Atturney-Generall, they do intend to oppoſe the ſaid reading and publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                     <p>Unto which <hi>de Bretigneres,</hi> for the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, hath ſaid, That their intent was not to do againſt what was agreed upon between them and the ſaid Counſellours of the citie, neither to withſtand the Ordinances of the ſaid Court, by which they were prohibited to uſe Amercements and Cenſures permitted by Law, for the maintaining of their Juriſdiction: and that the ſaid Letters-Patents were read in a due and lawfull manner.</p>
                     <p>The Court hath ordered, and doth now order, That in the margent at the <pb n="125" facs="tcp:121272:63"/> lower end of the ſaid Letters-Patents, theſe following words ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="endorsement">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Read, publiſhed and regiſtred, in the hearing of the Kings Atturney-Generall; the Contents thereof to be enjoyed and uſed by the Petitioners, according to the Edict of their ordaining and eſtabliſhing: a Decree being made thereupon; and another Ordinance being made between the Sheriff of</hi> Roan <hi>and them, in the moneth of</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember <hi>laſt paſt; and an Order between the Prior and Conſuls, and the Counſellours of the Common-hall of this Citie.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given as above.</dateline>
                        <signed>Signed <hi>Du Val,</hi> with his Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnature.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="letters_patent">
                  <p>BY the Kings Letters-Patents given at <hi>Angers</hi> the 6 of
<hi>November,</hi> 1568. it was permitted unto the ſaid Conſuls to levie Moneys upon Merchants dwelling and trafficking in the citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> either ſtrangers made Denizens, or others; as well for the buying of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121272:64"/> a place for their Court, as for other occaſions and things thereunto inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: and approved of in the Court of Parliament, the 2 day of <hi>May,</hi> in the yeer aforeſaid. The ſaid Letters-Patents, and the Ordinance of appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereof, are here omitted, for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſake, becauſe they are mentioned and related in the next following ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball Proceſſe.</p>
                  <div type="process">
                     <head>The verball Proceſſe made by the Counſellors deputed by the Court.</head>
                     <p>IN the yeer of the Lord 1566. on Friday the 2 of
<hi>Auguſt;</hi> We <hi>George le Brun,</hi> one of his Majeſties Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in his Court of Parliament at <hi>Roan,</hi> deputed Commiſſioner by it, by an Ordinance of the 26 day of <hi>June</hi> laſt; at the requeſt of <hi>Bardin Bignon</hi> the Atturney of the Merchants, and of the Exchange of the Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls of this city of <hi>Roan:</hi> and M. <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Godeffroy,</hi> Advocate in the ſaid Court, and chief Commiſſioner in the civill Regiſter in the Auditories of the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121272:64"/> Bayliffs and Sheriffs Courts in this city of
<hi>Roan:</hi> did go to put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the ſaid Ordinance, containing our Commiſſion; and, according unto it, to cauſe the Letters-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents to be read and publiſhed, and alſo the Ordinances of the ſaid Court mentioned therein. And firſt of all, in the Auditory of the Bayliffs, where we found the Court ſitting, and M. <hi>James de Brevedent,</hi> Lieutenant-Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall unto the ſaid Bailiff of <hi>Roan,</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, aſſiſted by M.
<hi>James de Chande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier, Richard Guerard, James Cadyot,</hi> and <hi>Robert le Teillers,</hi> counſellours in the Preſidiall See of the ſaid Bayliwick: which <hi>de Brevedent</hi> having yeelded us the chayr, we have, at the requeſt of the ſaid <hi>Bignon</hi> the Atturney, cauſed to be read and publiſhed by the ſaid <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deffroy</hi> our Regiſter, firſt of all the ſaid Decree containing our Commiſſion, and afterwards the ſaid Letters-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents given at <hi>Angers</hi> the 6 day of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> laſt, the Ordinance of the Court given for the approving and granting of them, the 2 day of <hi>May</hi> alſo laſt <pb n="128" facs="tcp:121272:65"/> paſt; the Letters-Patents given at <hi>Moulins</hi> the 22 day of <hi>February;</hi> the Ordinance of the Court given upon the reading, publiſhing and regiſtring of them, the 22 of <hi>March,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinance therein mentioned, given the eleventh day of <hi>December</hi> aforegoing, between the Sheriff of
<hi>Roan,</hi> of the one part, and the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of the other: to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Decree of the 22 of <hi>June</hi> laſt paſt, containing a Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from the ſaid Court, unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to cauſe the ſaid Letters and Ordinances to be publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſaid Juriſdictions and Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of the Bayliwick and Sherival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of
<hi>Roan:</hi> after which reading and publiſhing, the ſaid
<hi>Bignon,</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Name,</hi> hath required us, that an Act and a verball Proceſſe might be delivered unto him. And it hath been required and demanded, by the ſaid <hi>de Brevedent</hi> the Lieutenant, that the copies of the ſaid Letters and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances might be delivered unto him, to provide himſelf for his part, <pb n="122" facs="tcp:121272:65"/> againſt the uſurpations which the ſaid Prior and Conſuls make commonly upon the Juriſdiction, and otherwiſe, as he ſhall ſee good to be done; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, that the ſaid reading and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing can be no ways prejudiciall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. The like Requeſt and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation being made by M. <hi>Matthew Poullain,</hi> Advocate in the behalf of the Regiſters of the ſaid Bayliff of <hi>Roan,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Bignon</hi> proteſting againſt it, in the ſaid <hi>Name:</hi> Of which read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and publiſhing, we have granted an Act to the ſaid ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, appearing as above; and to the ſaid Lieutenants, and Regiſters of their Proteſtations; and to the ſaid <hi>Bignon</hi> in the ſaid Name, of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation to the contrary, to be availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unto them reſpectively, as it ſhall be reaſonable; and have ordered, that the copies of the ſaid Letters-Patents and Ordinances ſhould be delivered unto the ſaid <hi>Bevedent</hi> and Regiſter, to ſuch end as ſhall be fitting.</p>
                     <p>This being done, we went into the Sheriffs Auditory, wherein we have <pb n="130" facs="tcp:121272:66"/> likewiſe found the Court ſitting, and kept by M. <hi>William Puchot</hi> Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> who yeelded us the place and the chair: in which Auditory the Court ſitting as above, we have cauſed the like reading and publiſhing to be made, as above, of the Letters-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and Ordinances above quoted and dated: Which reading and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing being heard by the ſaid <hi>Bignon,</hi> he hath beſought and requeſted in the ſaid Name, that an Act, and a verball Proceſſe thereof, might be delivered unto him, to be available in time to come, as it ſhall be meet. And we were requeſted by the ſaid <hi>Puchot,</hi> to cauſe the copies of the ſaid Letters-Patents and Ordinances to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him, to provide himſelf for his part, againſt the uſurpations which he hath ſaid to be made daily by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls upon his Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and to that end, to preſent his Petition unto the Court, that it may be likewiſe permitted unto him to cauſe the ſaid Ordinance of regulating made between him and the ſaid Prior <pb n="131" facs="tcp:121272:66"/> and Conſuls, the 11 of
<hi>December,</hi> to be publiſhed, after the ſound of the Trumpet, in all the croſſe-ways of the City: proteſting moreover, that the ſaid reading and the publiſhing can be no ways prejudicial unto him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we have ordered, that the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall have, and we have granted them, an Act of the ſaid reading and publiſhing to ſuch ends as are contained in their requeſt, and unto the ſaid Sheriff his Proteſtation: and that the Copies requeſted by him ſhall be delivered unto him, to ſuch ends as it ſhall be meet, and unto the ſaid <hi>Bignon</hi> in the ſaid Name, of his contrary Proteſtation. Of all which things we have made this verball Proceſſe, and have ſigned it in truth with our Signet, and cauſed it to be ſigned by our Regiſter and Aſſiſtant, and thereunto the Seal of our own Arms to be put, the yeer and day above-written.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="letters_patent">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:121272:67"/>
                  <head>The Kings Letters-Patents, containing a Declaration, upon the reeſtabliſhing of Court of Requeſts in <hi>Roan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>CHarles</hi> by the grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <salute>To Our truſty and welbeloved keeping Our Court of Parliament at
<hi>Roan.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Whereas by the Ordinance of the reeſtabliſhing the Court of Requeſts in Our ſaid Court, publiſhed in it the firſt day of
<hi>July</hi> laſt, it was ordered in one of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles thereof, That the Maſters of the ſaid Requeſts ſhall take notice in the firſt inſtance privatively from any other, of the differences of <hi>Hanſians, Germanes, Oſtrelins, Engliſh, Scotch, Portingals, Spaniſh,</hi> and other Forreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which ſhall be made and moved by them againſt Our Subjects within the Precincts of your Juriſdiction, for what occaſion ſoever: which many would interpret to the prejudice and reſtraint of the Juriſdiction of the Prior and Conſuls of the Merchants of Our city of
<hi>Roan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:121272:67"/>We give you therefore to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, That upon the Remonſtrance made unto us by the Atturney of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to make Our intents and will clear; We have ſaid and declared, and do ſay and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, by theſe Preſents, That we have not meaned by the ſaid Article of the ſaid Ordinance to prejudice any ways, nor touch what is formerly granted by Our Ordinances, Orders and Declarations made upon the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of <hi>Roan,</hi> for Suits in Law, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between Merchants, and in matters of Merchandiſe, and in things incident thereunto. We will, and Our pleaſure is, That the ſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Orders and Declarations ſhall hold, be kept and obſerved in every point, without any reſtriction or limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſoever: the ſaid Article not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. Moreover, We do command and enjoyn you to cauſe the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, preſent or to come, to enjoy fully and peaceably the ſaid Letters-Patents and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121272:68"/> ending, and cauſing all hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances to the contrary to ceaſe. The Ordaining, and re-eſtabliſhing of the ſaid Chamber of Requeſts, or any oppoſitions, or prohibitions to the contrary thereof notwithſtanding; for ſuch is our pleaſure.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at the Castle of</hi> Bolonge
<hi>neer</hi> Paris
<date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 8. <hi>day of July, in the year of the Lord</hi> 1568. <hi>and the eighth year of our Reign.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed by the King in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell <hi>Camus,</hi> and ſealed upon a ſingle Labell with the great Seal of yellow-wax.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="confirmation">
                  <div type="body_of_confirmation">
                     <head>A Confirmation of the Ordinances and Declarations concerning the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Juriſdiction, and <hi>Common Place</hi> of the Merchants of <hi>Roan</hi> in the year <hi>1596.</hi> And Ordinance of the approbation thereof in Parliament.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>HEnry</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Navar,</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <salute>To all preſent and to come Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Our
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:121272:68"/> dear and well beloved, the Prior and Conſuls of the Merchants of our Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Roan,</hi> have cauſed to be Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated unto us, That although our deceaſed predeceſſours <hi>Charles</hi> and
<hi>Henry</hi> the laſt our moſt honoured Lords, Father in Law and brother, have for great and juſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations granted them Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents aſwell in form of Ordinances of their ordaining and Inſtitution, as of Orders, and Declarations, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Juriſdiction, and the taking notice of what is granted them in matters of Merchandize and for the manner of their Election duly and rightly approved of in our Court of Parliament of the ſaid place: never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe they are dayly troubled and tormented by Judges in Ordinary, which endeavour to make the ſaid Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of no effect, and to fruſtrate the Merchants of the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> their Widdows, Heires, and Factors, Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiators, Maſters of Ships &amp; of Veſſels, Boats, &amp; Packmen, Carriers carrying and re-carrying their Merchandizes,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121272:69"/> importing or tranſporting their Wares by water and by land; of the good and ſincere intention of our ſaid Predeceſſors, and there are alſo Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of appeals iſſued out of the Chancery in the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> for ſmall ſums under which they have power to Judge without any appeal. And moreover, Sergeants do not perform and execute what they are enjoyned by the ſaid Ordinances and Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and other treſpaſſes made upon their Juriſdiction; by reaſon of which and that we may cauſe them to enjoy peaceably the contents of the ſaid Ordinances and Declarations, Dated in the Moneth of <hi>March</hi> 1556. 23 of
<hi>October</hi> 1563. 29 of <hi>December</hi> 1564. 22 of <hi>February</hi>
1566. 22 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1586. and of the Ordinances of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probations thereof, which have enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our ſaid Court of Parliament: they have beſought us to be pleaſed to grant them our neceſſary Letters Pattents of confirmation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſiring to redreſſe the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in this point, and to afford all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions <pb n="137" facs="tcp:121272:69"/> unto Merchants to cauſe the commerce and traffick to flouriſh, as much as it ſhall lye in us, in imitation of our ſaid Predeceſſours, and for the Common good of this our Kingdome We have continued and confirmed, do continue and confirme by theſe Preſents, all the Contents of the ſaid Ordinances, Orders, and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſaid Kings our Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and of the ſaid approbations made by our ſaid Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning them, here annexed againſt the Counter-ſeal of our Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery, that they and their ſucceſſours in the ſaid charges, may enjoy them, and make uſe of them, as they have done heretofore, and do yet at this preſent, altogether and in the ſame form and manner as it is contained at large, and declared in the ſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Orders, and Declarations, and in the ſaid Ordinances of appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thereof. Moreover, we do charge and command our truſty and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved the Councellours, keeping out Court of Parliament in the ſaid
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:121272:70"/> 
                        <hi>Roan,</hi> the maſters of Requeſts in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary of our hall, keeping the Seal of our ſaid Chancery, and unto them that keep the Court of Requeſts of our ſaid Court, the Bailiff of the ſaid
<hi>Roan,</hi> or his Lieutenant, and to every one of them, as it ſhall concern them, to verifie or approve of theſe our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Letters of continuation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and of all the contents thereof of the ſaid Declarations, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and approbations thereof granted and made by the ſaid Kings our Predeceſſors, to cauſe, ſuffer and permit the ſaid Petitioners, and their ſucceſſours in the ſaid charges, fully, peaceably, and perpetually to enjoy and uſe them; ceaſing and cauſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to ceaſe from all troubles, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances, and oppoſitions to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. For ſuch is our pleaſure, and that it may be a ſure, and a permanent thing for ever, we have cauſed our Seal to be put unto theſe preſents, our own right, being ſaved in this, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens right in all things.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <date>
                              <hi>in the yeer of our
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121272:70"/> Lord</hi> 1569. <hi>and the eighth year of our reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed <hi>Henry,</hi>
                        </signed> and upon the fold of the Labell,
<signed>By the King. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier,</signed> with his Subſignature.</closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="seal">
                     <p>Moreover it is written thus upon the fold, or place of the Labell, <hi>Viſa Contentor.</hi> Signed <hi>Pouſſepin</hi> with his ſubſignature, and ſealed upon a labell of red and green ſilke, with the great Seal of green wax; and beſides Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the Regiſters of the Court, in the hearing, and with the conſent of the Kings Atturney Generall, to the end, that they which have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, may enjoy the Contents thereof according to their form and tenour, and according to the former Ordinances.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in the Parliament</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 7. <hi>day of</hi> Auguſt,
1598.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed</hi> De Boiſleueſque</signed> 
                        <hi>with his Subſignature.</hi>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="140" facs="tcp:121272:71"/>
                  <head>An Extract out of the Regiſter of the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Petition preſented by the Prior and Conſuls of this City of <hi>Roan;</hi> to the end that the Letters Pattens granted unto them in the moneth of <hi>December</hi> 1596. may be verified and approved of, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in the Regiſters of the Court, to enjoy the Contents thereof accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their form and tenour, by which the King hath confirmed unto them all the Contents of thoſe Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and Ordinances, which were made by his Predeceſſors in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of <hi>March</hi> 1556. the 23. of
<hi>October</hi> 563. the 29. of <hi>December</hi> 564. the 22. of
<hi>February</hi> 566. and the 22. of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 586. together with the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and acceptations thereof by the ſaid Court, that they and their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in the ſaid Offices, may enjoy and uſe them, as they have done here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and do ſtill uſe at this preſent,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121272:71"/> and in the ſame form and manner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together, as it is contained and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the ſaid Declarations, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Ordinances concerning the approbations thereof. The ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being ſeen by the Court, together with the Letters Pattents in form of a Declaration of King
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond in the moneth of <hi>March</hi> 1556. The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the ſaid Court enſuing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the approbation thereof, on the
20. of <hi>July</hi> 563. other Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens of <hi>Charls</hi> the ninth of the 25. of <hi>October</hi> in the ſame year, and the 29. of
<hi>December</hi> 564. An Ordinance en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued upon the approbation thereof, of the 30. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 566. Other Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Pattents of Declaration, of the 22. of <hi>February</hi> in the ſaid year 66. An Ordinance of approbation of the 22. of <hi>March,</hi> other Letters Pattens in form of a Declaration, granted to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, by King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of happy memory, lately deceaſed: In the moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 586. upon the Ordinance enſued for the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the ſaid Letters Pattents of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121272:72"/> the 22. of the ſaid Moneth, after the Concluſion of the Kings Atturney Generall. All being conſidered, the Court hath ordered, and doth order, that the ſaid Lettets Pattens of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the moneth of <hi>December</hi> 596. ſhall be Regiſtred in the Regiſter of the ſaid Court, That the Prior and the Conſuls of the Merchants of this city of
<hi>Roan,</hi> may enjoy the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof, according as it is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the former Ordinances.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in the ſaid Court of Parliament</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 7. <hi>day of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,
1598.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <hi>The Coppies being compared with the Originall.</hi>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>De Boiſleueſque</hi> with his Subſignature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="confirmation">
                  <head>Another Confirmation of the ſaid Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Place of Merchants in <hi>Roan,</hi> and the approbation thereof in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
                  <div type="body_of_confirmation">
                     <opener>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>LEwis</hi> by the grace of God, King of
<hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navar,</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <salute>To all preſent <pb n="143" facs="tcp:121272:72"/> and to come, Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Deſiring, in imitation, and after the example of the deceaſed Kings our predeceſſours, to ſhew our grace and favour unto our dear and welbeloved the Prior and the Conſuls of the Merchants in our good City of <hi>Roan,</hi> and to maintain and protect them with all our might, in the Conſulary Juriſdiction, which was granted unto them by our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, by many of their Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; confirmed alſo by the Letters-Patents of Charter of the moneth of <hi>December,</hi> of our moſt honoured Lord and Father, in the yeer 96. After which, many Judgements and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances have enſued to their profit and advantage, that the ſaid Juriſdiction might no ways, and in what manner ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, be altered or diminiſhed to their prejudice.</p>
                     <p>For theſe cauſes, by the advice of our Councell, who have ſeen the ſaid Letters-Patents, Judgements and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances annexed hereunto. We, out of our ſpeciall grace, full power, and Royall authority, have continued and <pb n="144" facs="tcp:121272:73"/> confirmed, do continue and confirm unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of Merchants in the ſaid City of <hi>Roan;</hi> granted, given and confirmed unto them by the ſaid Letters-Patents and Ordinances, to be enjoyed and uſe made of by the ſaid Petitioners, and by their Succeſſours in the ſaid Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, fully and peaceably, according unto their ſaid Letters Patents, Grants, Judgements and Ordinances, and in the ſame manner as they have well and rightly enjoyed and uſed them, and do ſtill at this preſent make uſe thereof. Moreover, we do com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our truſtie and welbeloved kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping our Parliament in <hi>Roan,</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Requeſts in Ordinary in our Common-hall, the keepers of the Seal of the Chancery, and thoſe that keep the Requeſts in the Hall or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of the ſaid place, the Bayliff of the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> or his Lieutenant, and every one of them, as it ſhall concern them, to cauſe, ſuffer and permit the ſaid petitioners and their ſucceſſours in the ſaid places, to enjoy, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, <pb n="146" facs="tcp:121272:73"/> fully, and perpetually, to make uſe thereof in every point according to their form and tenour of theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Pattens of confirmation, and all the Contents as above, and ſo to cauſe our aboveſaid Letters Patents, Declarations and Ordinances made thereupon, to be kept, obſerved, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and put in execution, not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting nor ſuffering the leaſt trouble, diſturbance, or hinderance to be done unto them to the contrary.</p>
                     <p>Which we do expreſly forbid unto all perſons upon 100.
<abbr>l.</abbr> amercement, and upon all the charges, dammages, and intereſts; for ſuch is our pleaſure. And that it may be a ſure and a perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent thing for ever, We have cauſed our Seal to be put unto theſe preſents, ſave our own right in theſe, and the right of others in all things.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Roan
<date>
                              <hi>in the year of our Lord,</hi> 1617. <hi>and the eight year of our Reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="seal">
                     <p>Signed <hi>Lewis,</hi> and upon the Labell <hi>Viſa,</hi> and <hi>Contentor:</hi> ſigned <hi>Thibaut</hi> with his ſubſignature. The ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <pb n="147" facs="tcp:121272:74"/> being ſealed with the great Seal of green wax, with red and green ſtrings.</p>
                     <p>And Regiſtred, the Kings Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Generall hearing, and aſſenting unto them, that they that have obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, may enjoy the Contents thereof according to the former Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in Parliament</hi>
                           <date>the 14. day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1618.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed <hi>Cuſſon</hi> with his ſubſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>An Extract out of the Regiſter of the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Petition preſented by the Priors and Conſuls, and the Atturney of Merchants of this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> to the end that the Letters Pattents in form of Charters given at <hi>Roan</hi> in the moneth of
<hi>December</hi> laſt, may be verified and approved of, and Regiſtred in the Regiſters of the <pb n="147" facs="tcp:121272:74"/> Court: that they that have obtained them, may enjoy the Contents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, according to their form and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Court having ſeen the ſaid Petition, the Letters Pattens by which the King) having ſeen at the Councell Table, many other Letters Pattens of the Kings his predeceſſors Charters, Judgements, and Ordinances enſued) hath continued and confirmed the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, that they and their ſucceſſors in the ſaid charges, may keep it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it, according and conforming to their ſaid Letters: and even as they have heretofore well and rightly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed them, and made uſe thereof, and do ſtill at this preſent make uſe of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>The Letters Pattents in form of a Declaration of
<hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond of the moneth of <hi>March</hi> 1556. contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ordaining and eſtabliſhing of the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls. The Ordinances of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation thereof, in the ſaid Court of the 20 of <hi>July</hi> 1563. Other Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <pb n="148" facs="tcp:121272:75"/> Pattents of
<hi>Charles</hi> the ninth of the 13. of <hi>October,</hi> in the ſaid year of the 29. of <hi>December</hi> 1564. The Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances upon the approbation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of of the 30. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1566. Other Letters of Declaration of the 22. of <hi>February</hi> in the ſaid year, and an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of approbation, of the 22. of <hi>March.</hi> Other Letters Pattents in form of a Declaration of the moneth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1586. and another Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance enſued thereupon, of the 22. of the ſaid moneth. Other Letters of King
<hi>Henry</hi> the Great, of the moneth of <hi>December</hi> 1596. containing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of all the ſaid Ordinances and Declarations. An Ordinance of the ſaid Court of the 17. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1598. made upon the approving of the ſaid Letters Pattents: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Kings Atturney Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and the relation of the Deputy Councellour deputed by the Court. All theſe things being heard, the ſaid Court with conſent of the ſaid At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney Generall; Hath ordered and doth order, that the ſaid Letters Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents <pb n="149" facs="tcp:121272:75"/> of the ſaid moneth of <hi>December</hi> laſt paſt: ſhall be Regiſtred in the Regiſter thereof; that they, which have obtained them, may enjoy what is contained therein, according to the former Ordinances.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in the ſaid Court of Parliament</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 14. <hi>day of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt in the year</hi>
1618.</date> 
                        <hi>The Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py being compared with their Originals.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Culſon</hi> with his Subſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="ordinance_of_Privy_Council">
                  <p>An Ordinance of his Majeſties Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Councell, containing a prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made unto the Clarks Audiencia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and Controllers of the Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Roan,</hi> to iſſue forth any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion or Writ of appeal from thoſe ſentences given by the Prior and Conſuls, that ſhall not exceed 250. <abbr>l.</abbr> upon nullity and no Validity thereof. And they are enjoyned to inſert in the Commiſſions or Writs of appeal the Date of the ſaid ſentences, and the ſums likewiſe from which the appeal is made.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:121272:76"/>
                  <head>An extract out of the Regiſters of the Kings Privy Councell.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Petition preſented unto the King in his Privy Councell by the Prior and Conſuls of <hi>Roan,</hi> to the end, that whereas by the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing and inſtitution of their Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, in imitation, and after the manner of that of the Conſuls of <hi>Paris:</hi> they have Authority to Judge without appeal, as far as 500. <abbr>l.</abbr> The Court of Parliament hath notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding limited the ſaid Authority unto
250. <abbr>l.</abbr> after the manner of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidiall Courts, which the ſaid Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners have alwayes enjoyed, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few yeers, that Merchants ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves condemned to pay any ſmall ſums as of 50.
<abbr>l.</abbr> and of 100. crowns, or of 120. <abbr>l.</abbr> do appeal from their ſentences, and addreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Clarks of Chancery, which for the moſt part ſet not down the ſums contained in the ſaid ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <pb n="151" facs="tcp:121272:76"/> nor the date thereof, which is the reaſon why the Petitioners, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly intimated and cited by the ſaid appeals. That it may therefore pleaſe his Majeſtie to maintaine and uphold the Petitioners in the Authority they have to Judge without appeal as far as 500.
<abbr>l.</abbr> and to order that ſuch ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences as ſhall go beyond the ſaid ſum, may be put in execution, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, or appeals whatſoever not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof, and to prohibit all or any of the Clarks, Audienciaries and other Officers of the Chancery to ſigne, or cauſe to be ſealed any Commiſſion of appeal from the ſaid ſentences of the ſaid Petitioners upon 200. <abbr>l.</abbr> amercement in their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate names, and which contain not the ſums and the Date mentioned therein, and to enjoyn the Court of Parliament to take no notice of ſuch appeals, but to ſend the parties back again preſently, and to amerce thoſe that ſhall appeal.</p>
                  <p>The ſaid Petition being ſeen, the <pb n="152" facs="tcp:121272:77"/> copie of the Declaration of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of the Juriſdiction of the Conſuls of <hi>Paris</hi> of the moneth of <hi>November,</hi> 1563. the copie of the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters-Patents in form of a Declaration, containing the Inſtitution of the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, after the manner of that of <hi>Paris,</hi> of the 29 of <hi>December,</hi> 1564. the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Court of Parliament of <hi>Roan</hi> of the 30 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1566. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the approving of the ſaid De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, upon that condition, That the ſaid Conſuls ſhall not take notice or judge of Cauſes, without appeal, beyond and further then the Judges of Preſidiall Courts uſe to do. Other Letters-Patents containing an order and regulating of the ſaid Conſulary Juriſdiction of <hi>Paris,</hi> of the 20 of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
1566. The Sentences given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of <hi>Roan:</hi> A copie of the Commiſſion of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from thoſe Sentences, with the Warrants and Citations of the ſaid Conſuls before the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Roan,</hi> to ſee the ſaid Sentences <pb n="153" facs="tcp:121272:77"/> corrected and amended: and other Papers annexed to the ſaid Petition: And the Relation of the Counſellour deputed by the Court for that purpoſe being heard; the King in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell ordereth, That this Ordinance ſhall be put in execution, according to the Decree and Ordinance of the approving of the Parliament of <hi>Roan</hi> thereof; and ſo, that Sentences given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding 250 <hi>l.</hi> ſhall be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, notwithſtanding oppoſitions or appeals whatſoever, hath prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Clerks, Audienciaries, and Controllers of the Chancery of
<hi>Roan,</hi> to iſſue out any Commiſſions of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal from the ſaid Sentences; and charged them to inſert henceforwards in the ſaid Commiſſions, the dates of the ſaid Sentences, and the ſums con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, with the penalty of the damages, and intereſts of the ſaid parties, in their own private name, for their own particular, and of greater loſſe, if it falleth out ſo.</p>
                  <p>And this preſent Ordinance ſhall <pb n="154" facs="tcp:121272:78"/> be read in the Chancery on a Seal-day, leſt the Officers of the Chancery ſhould pretend to be ignorant thereof. The Atturney-Generall of the ſaid Court is charged to aid and aſſiſt the execution of the ſaid Declaration, and of this preſent Ordinance.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given in his Majeſties Privie Councell ſitting in</hi> Paris,
<date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 17 <hi>day of</hi> March,
1618.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <hi>The copies being compared with their Originall.</hi>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>de la Grange</hi> with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignature and Signet.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="decree">
                  <div type="body_of_decree">
                     <opener>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>LEwis</hi> by the grace of God, King of
<hi>France</hi> and of <hi>Navar,</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <salute>To all our Truſtie and Welbeloved the Counſellours keeping our Court of Parliament in <hi>Roan,</hi> Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>We command, order, and expreſly enjoyn you, to cauſe to be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution the Ordinance of our Councel here annexed under our counter-Seal, given this day upon the Petition pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented unto us by our welbeloved the <pb n="155" facs="tcp:121272:78"/> Prior and Conſuls of our citie of
<hi>Roan,</hi> in every point according to the form and tenour thereof; conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and cauſing to be conſtrained, in our Name, all ſuch as ſhall ſuffer themſelves to be conſtrained to do it, to ſuffer and obey it, by all due, right and juſt ways, oppoſitions or appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever notwithſtanding. We do likewiſe command the firſt of our welbeloved Counſellours and Maſters of Requeſts in ordinary of our Hall, that ſhall be found in thoſe places, or in any Audienciary of the Chancery of <hi>Roan,</hi> to cauſe the ſaid Ordinance to be read and publiſhed in the Chancery on a Seal-day, that the Officers thereof may not plead
<hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus:</hi> charging to that effect our At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney-Generall to aid and uphold the execution of the ſaid Ordinance, and of the Declaration mentioned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. We do moreover charge and command our firſt Purſuivant or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant required thereof, to ſignifie our ſaid Ordinance unto the ſaid Officers of the Chancery, and to all others <pb n="156" facs="tcp:121272:79"/> whom it ſhall concern, making unto them, in our name, the Inhibitions and Prohibitions contained therein: and for the full and entire execution of our ſaid Ordinance, to ſerve all other Warrants and Acts requiſite and neceſſary, without asking any leave or <hi>Pareatis</hi> to that purpoſe: For, ſuch is our pleaſure, notwithſtanding any clamour of <hi>Haero</hi> Charter of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie,</hi> and Letters contrary unto it.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Paris
<date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 27 <hi>day of</hi> March, <hi>in the yeer of the Lord,</hi> 1618. <hi>and the</hi> 8 <hi>yeer of Our Reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed by the King in his Councell: <hi>de la Grange</hi> with his Subſignature, and ſealed upon a ſingle Label of the Great Scal of yellow Wax. And underneath in the ſide of the Margent, it is written:</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="endorsement">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Read, publiſhed, regiſtred in the Chancery of</hi> Roan, <hi>on a Seal day, before us,</hi> John Hallé <hi>Lord of</hi> Monflaines, <hi>his Majesties Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of his Privie Councel, and of his Councell of State, and Maſter of Requeſts in Ordinary, of his Hall,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:121272:79"/> that the Contents thereof may be kept according to their form and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>Given on Tueſday the 28 day of
<hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1618.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed</hi> Hallé <hi>with his Subſignature.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>An Extract out of the Regiſter of the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Petition preſented by the Prior, Conſuls, and by the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney of the Merchants of the citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> to the end that the Ordinance of the Privie Councell, and the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters-Patents given preſently after it, of the 17 day of <hi>March</hi> laſt, may be regiſtred in the Regiſters of the Court: That the contents thereof may be put in execution, according to their form and tenour: and to that end, to charge one of the Purſuivants to ſignifie them unto the Officers of the Chancery: and that the ſaid Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance and Letters may be read, that they may not plead, <hi>Ignoramus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſaid Petition being ſeen by the Court, and the ſaid Ordinance of the <pb n="158" facs="tcp:121272:80"/> 17 of <hi>March,</hi> by which it was ordered, that the Declaration of the ordaining and eſtabliſhing of the Juriſdiction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall be put in execuiton, according to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the approbation of the ſaid Court, and ſo, that Sentences and Judgements given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, not exceeding the ſum of 205<abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> ſhall be put in execution; oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or whatſoever notwithſtanding. And inhibition is made to the Clerks, Audienciaries, and Controllers of the Chancery of <hi>Roan,</hi> to iſſue forth any Writs or Commiſſions of appeal from the ſaid Sentences: and they are charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to inſert henceforward in the ſaid Writs of Appeal the date of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and the ſums contained in them, upon the penalty of damages and intereſts of the parties in their own private name, and for their own particular. And that the ſaid Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſhall be read in the ſaid Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cery on a Seal day, that the ſaid Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers thereof may not plead, <hi>Ignoramus.</hi> The ſaid Letters of <hi>March,</hi> of the
17 <pb n="159" facs="tcp:121272:80"/> of <hi>March,</hi> given immediately after the ſaid Ordinance: The concluſion of Kings Atturney-Generall, and the Commiſſioners being heard, the ſaid Court hath granted an Act unto the ſaid Prior, Conſuls, and to the Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of Merchants: of the preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid Letters, and of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Councell. And hath ordered, that a copie thereof ſhall remain in the Regiſters Office of the ſaid Court, that they may be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration, as it ſhall be meet.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at</hi> Roan, <hi>in the ſaid Court of Parliament,</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 14 <hi>of</hi> Auguſt, 1618.</date> 
                        <hi>The Copies being compared with their Originall.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Cuſſon,</hi> with his Subſignature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <p>Out of the Paper of the Articles of the Remonſtrance made in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the three Eſtates of <hi>Normandy</hi> ſitting at
<hi>Roan,</hi> the 16 of <hi>September,</hi> 1613. Together out of the Anſwers and Ordinances made thereupon, by the King at <hi>Paris</hi> the 22 of <hi>January</hi> 
                     <pb n="160" facs="tcp:121272:81"/> next after following, 1614. was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted the following Article.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="22" type="article">
                              <head>The XXII. Article.</head>
                              <p>THe calling in of the Controlls of Titles, is demanded. All manner of perſons are intereſſed in it, and more eſpecially Merchants, for Bonds conceived to be made for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, which require a ſpeedy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch, as well for forrain Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, as for them that are tranſported from one Country into another; ſuch unprofitable expences being needleſſe in trading; underneath which Article the words are written.
<hi>To the King. And that the Commiſsioners are agreed on.</hi> Moreover,
<hi>Granted upon paying again what is disburſed. And in the Interim, the Kings intent is not, That the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trols ſhould be of any effect for the Bills of Exchange, and promiſes between Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Out of another paper of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles <pb n="161" facs="tcp:121272:81"/> of the Remonſtrances made in the Aſſembly of the three Eſtates of
<hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy</hi> ſitting at <hi>Roan</hi> the 18. day of
<hi>September,</hi> 1614. together out of the Anſwer and Ordinance made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, by his Majeſty at <hi>Paris</hi> the 29. of <hi>January</hi>
1615. was extracted the 17. following Article.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div n="17" type="article">
                              <head>The XVII. Article.</head>
                              <p>ALthough by the Anſwer given unto the Eſtates aſſembled the laſt year, your Majeſty did grant us, That the Controule of <hi>Titres</hi> ſhould be of no more effect, for Bills of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, and promiſes between Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, becauſe the freedome of traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick doth require that the ſtrictneſſe of formalities may not be ſo exact in ſuch kinds of Agreements, as it muſt be in others. Nevertheleſſe upon a meere Requeſt preſented by Maſter <hi>Champage,</hi> Captain of
<hi>Fointaine-belleau:</hi> pretending to have a Pattentee for the ſaid Controuls; he hath obtained an Ordinance of the 24. of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:121272:82"/> by which the Anſwer given to the ſaid Eſtates is called in: and it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto the ſaid <hi>Champagne,</hi> and to his Farmers, to get themſelves paid for the Controule upon the ſaid Bills of Exchange, and promiſes between Merchants. In caſe this ſhould take effect, it were to make all Illuſory, which was reſolved in your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, upon the Juſt demands of your people: and the Anſwers alſo, which your Majeſty was pleaſed to give them (which ought to be held holy, and kept inviolably) and to turn them into ſmoak. May it therefore pleaſe your Majeſty to Order, That the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto the Paper of the laſt year concerning Bills of Exchange, and promiſes between Merchants, be put in execution.</p>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <p>Vnderneath the which Article, theſe words are written,
<q> 
                        <hi>To the King, And the Commiſsioners are agreed upon it.</hi> Moreover, The Kings pleaſure is, that his Anſwer given upon this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to the 22. Article of the Paper which the Petitioners preſented unto
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:121272:82"/> him the laſt year, ſhall be put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>An Extract out of the Regiſters of the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>THe Court hath ſeen the Letters Pattents given at
<hi>Paris</hi> the 22. of <hi>January</hi> 1614, by which the King commandeth and doth order that the anſwer made by him the ſaid day, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the 22. Article of the Paper of the Remonſtrances, thoſe of the three Eſtates of the Country and Dutchy of <hi>Normandy,</hi> concerning the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule of Titres, be put in execution, kept, and obſerved according to the forme and tenour thereof: the extract of the 22. Article containing the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the controule of <hi>Titres,</hi> deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the States aboveſaid, with the Anſwer of the ſaid Lord. That he granted the ſaid Article upon repaying of the charges: and in the Interim that the intent of the ſaid Lord our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign is not, that the ſaid Controule <pb n="164" facs="tcp:121272:83"/> ſhall be of any effect for Bills of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, and for promiſes between Merchants of another extract of the 17. Article of another Paper of the Remonſtrances of the ſaid States, anſwered by the King the 29. of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> laſt concerning the former. The Kings Atturny Generall his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and the relation of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour choſen Commiſſioner for that purpoſe, being heard. The ſaid Court hath ordered with the conſent of the Atturney Generall, and doth Order that the ſaid Letters Patents, and the extracts of the ſaid Articles of the Remonſtrances of the ſaid Eſtates ſhall be Regiſtred in the Regiſters thereof: that the Contents of them may be put in execution, kept, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved according to their form, and tenour.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in the ſaid Court of Parliament</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 24. <hi>day of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember in the year,</hi>
1615.</date>
                     </dateline> 
                     <hi>The Copies being compared with their Originall.</hi>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:121272:83"/>
                  <head>Ordinances and ſentences given after the Ordinances and Declarations of the Juriſdiction of the Priour and Conſuls of the Merchants at <hi>Roan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the year of our Lord 1567. on Saturday the 26. of
<hi>Aprill,</hi> the Court ſitting: the Prior and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls of
<hi>Roan</hi> being afore us; when the Atturney of the <hi>Place, Exchange,</hi> and Juriſdiction of the Merchants in <hi>Roan,</hi> had cauſed to be cited <hi>James Du Fay</hi> Merchant, living is this City to be warned, that he might be amerced, by reaſon of removing and transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their Juriſdiction, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings Declaration, and the Ordinances of the Court; he had transferred this Juriſdiction, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded afore the Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Lieutenant, <hi>Jeſſe de Cauvigny</hi> Merchant in this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> upon the aſſignation, warning given in the roome of the ſaid <hi>Cauvigny</hi> unto the ſaid
<hi>Du Fay,</hi> for the payment of 8. <pb n="166" facs="tcp:121272:84"/> or ten barrils ſold unto him by the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> and ſince ſold again by the ſaid <hi>Du Fay,</hi> unto Maſter <hi>John Du Monſtier,</hi> Advocate in the Sheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valty of this City, to ſhun the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid barrils; the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> had declared unto the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney Generall, in the ſaid Sherival<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the ſaid citation and diſagreement of the parties ariſing out of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize between Merchant and Merchant, and according that ſame denounciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and intimation, the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney Generall, hath obtained an Injunction and Warrant of the ſaid Sheriff, by vertue whereof he made a prohibition unto the ſaid <hi>Jeſſe de Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigny</hi> to plead any where elſe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Sheriff: and he being ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to appear on the 23. day of this preſent moneth, before the ſaid She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff, which was the day of the aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given at the Inſtance of the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> to the ſaid <hi>De Fay,</hi> at which day the 23. the Kings Atturny had obtained a default againſt the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> in the ſaid Sheriffs Court, <pb n="167" facs="tcp:121272:84"/> and it was ordered that he ſhould be forced by an <hi>habeas corpus,</hi> to appear to anſwer the demands and concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſaid Atturney Generall and moreover at the inſtance of the ſaid Atturney Generall, was ſent for and carried before the Worſhipfull <hi>Laurence Puchot,</hi> Lord of <hi>Gerpon ville,</hi> and Sheriff of <hi>Roan, James Grenier</hi> his Majeſties Sergeant in this City, for the citation made afore the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and that the ſaid
<hi>Grenier</hi> was amerced 10. <abbr>l.</abbr> and committed to priſon to cloſe impriſonment, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the full payment of the ſaid ſum, ſo that to ſhun the impriſonment of his perſon, he was conſtrained to lay the ſaid amercement in the hands of <hi>Goſſelin</hi> a Sergeant, as it appeareth by his bill of receipt, bearing the Date of the 23. of this Inſtant moneth and year, deſiring that the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> ſhould purge and cleer himſelf if he had not bought the ſaid 8. Barrils, and ſince ſold them again unto the ſaid <hi>Du Monſtier,</hi> and if he was not a Merchant trading and trafficking in <pb n="168" facs="tcp:121272:85"/> Wines, and in Linnen cloaths and in other commodities, and if being in <hi>Maillotz</hi> ſtreet neer
<hi>Renelle,</hi> upon the warning which the ſaid <hi>Grenier</hi> gave him, at the inſtance of the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> to appear before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and that upon this he, the ſaid <hi>Du Fay,</hi> had deſired and declared unto the ſaid <hi>Grenier</hi> Sergeant, that he intended to plead before the ſaid Sheriff, and not before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, and that according to this, the ſaid <hi>Grenier</hi> had made his relation thereof unto the ſaid <hi>Du Fay.</hi> The Petition of the ſaid, <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> in the granting whereof we have taken and admitted of the oath of the ſaid <hi>Du Fay,</hi> who hath ſaid ſworn, and affirmed, acknowledged, and confeſſed; that he had bought of the ſaid
<hi>De Cavigny,</hi> the ſaid eight Barrills to ſell again, and that they were by him ſold again unto the ſaid <hi>Du Monſtier,</hi> of which oath and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, a letter was granted unto the ſaid Atturny of the Merchants, and the ſaid <hi>Du Fay,</hi> according to his
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:121272:85"/> confeſſion, and the advice of the Merchants there preſent; was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to pay for the ſaid Barrils after the rate of 11.
<hi>ſols,</hi> 6. <hi>deniers</hi> a peece; there being deduced out of that a
<hi>teſton;</hi> which the ſaid <hi>Cauvigny</hi> had received of the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> upon the ſaid ſum, and the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> was amerced an hundred <hi>ſols tournois</hi> for removing of and transferring the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, appliable according to the Ordinance with a reſtitution as well unto the ſaid <hi>Grenier</hi> Sergeant of the amercement, unto which he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned upon impriſonment of his body, by the ſaid Sheriff, as even alſo to the Intereſts, as well of the ſaid
<hi>Grenier,</hi> as of the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the charges of the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> taxed to the ſum of 40.
<hi>ſols</hi> ſix <hi>deniers fournois</hi> theſe preſent being comprehended, and the firſt Purſuivant or his Majeſties Sergeant required thereof, is charged, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to put theſe preſents in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.
<hi>Given as above.</hi> Signed <hi>Hallé, a marke and his Subſignature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="170" facs="tcp:121272:86"/>In the year of our Lord 1567. next following after the Declaration, on Saturday 26. day of <hi>Aprill</hi> in the morning in the hall of the King our Lord and Soveraigne at <hi>Roan,</hi> before us <hi>Laurence Puchot</hi> Eſquire Lord of <hi>Gerponuille,</hi> and Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our Order, and verball proceſſe made by us unto <hi>Thomas Pouppart</hi> the Kings Sergeant in this City of
<hi>Roan,</hi> to cauſe to appear in perſon, and to bring <hi>coram nobis, Jeſſé de Cauvigny</hi> a wine Merchant dwelling in <hi>Perchere ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Cooper</hi> this City, the ſaid <hi>Poupart</hi> Sergeant hath preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought before us the ſaid <hi>De Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigny,</hi> to anſwer unto the Concluſions of the Kings Atturney Generall, and to be amerced, becauſe he had requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and cauſed to be cited by <hi>James Grenier,</hi> the Kings Sergeant in the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> one <hi>James du Fay,</hi> Taylor, living in <hi>Perchere</hi> ſtreet, to appear the next day after before the Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, to pay him for eight Barrils, which is a transferring of Juriſdiction <pb n="171" facs="tcp:121272:86"/> againſt the Ordinance of the Court of Parliament, given between us and the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, ſo that by a ſentence given by us on Wedneſday laſt, the ſaid
<hi>Grenier</hi> was fined 10. <abbr>l.</abbr> and inhibition was made unto the ſaid <hi>Du Fay,</hi> then preſent at the giving of Judgement, to anſwer and conteſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame action before the Prior and Conſuls, and moreover there was an injunction granted unto the Kings Atturney, to cauſe the ſaid <hi>De Cauvig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> to be warned to appear and to be amerced for the transferring of Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; and ſince the ſaid <hi>De Cauvig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> was warned, he had appeared by his wife, which was many times en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to cauſe her husband to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and yet had not regarded it, and in the Interim had ſtill purſued the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, where this morning the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> having appeared before them, he was amerced one hundred <hi>ſols,</hi> and condemned to reſtore the ſaid 10. <abbr>l.</abbr> amercement, unto which the ſaid <hi>Grenier</hi> was condemned by, the ſaid <pb n="172" facs="tcp:121272:87"/> Wedneſday laſt, as the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> hath atteſted before us juſt now. The ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> being heard there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, who hath acknowledged, that he did require, and did cauſe the ſaid citation to be made before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls for the aforeſaid cauſe, but that he was not the Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the purſuit and ſentence given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Du Fay,</hi> but that it was rather at the inſtance of the Atturney of the Exchange of the Merchants in the ſaid Juriſdiction; the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> ſaying, moreover, that at the inſtance of the ſaid Atturney, he was prohibited to appear and to anſwere before us in the ſaid cauſe, as he did make it appear by the coppie of the ſaid Warrant of inhibition, and by Mr. <hi>Jean de Laudaſsi</hi> the ſecurity, as being the moſt ancient Advocate in the abſence of Kings Atturny Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall in this Court of the Sheriff. It was required, that notwithſtanding the allegations; and Remonſtrances of the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> he might be <pb n="173" facs="tcp:121272:87"/> condemned to 10.
<abbr>l.</abbr> amercement for the transferring of Juriſdiction, and to the Juriſdiction of the amercement unto which the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> was amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls: whereupon advice being taken of the aſſiſtants, it was ſaid according unto it, that the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> for the transferring of Juriſdiction, and for the contempt of Juſtice, ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merced 10. <abbr>l.</abbr> and condemned to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ſum of one hundred <hi>ſols,</hi> and all to which the ſaid <hi>Du Fay</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, conſidering the inhibitions which were made unto him, ſpeaking to his wife, for which amercement it was ordered that the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> ſhould be kept cloſe priſoner unto the full payment thereof, and to that end committed to the cuſtody of the ſaid <hi>Poupart</hi> Sergeant, from which the ſaid
<hi>De Cauvigny</hi> hath declared that he did appeal, notwithſtanding the which appeal and without any prejudice un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, We have ordered that he ſhall forthwith pay the ſaid amercements <pb n="174" facs="tcp:121272:88"/> from which the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> hath declared again, that he did appeal and did take us to parties, ſaying, that he had Letters to that purpoſe, which he had got in the Chancery of <hi>Roan,</hi> which he ſhewed; uſing theſe words, We ſhall meet with you well enough, with an incivill countenance, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof, and becauſe the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> hath taken us to partie, by which he hath declared again that he did perſiſt, we have ceaſed from taking any further notice of this cauſe, and forthwith required Maſter <hi>Robert Anfrye,</hi> as being the ancienteſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate in this Court, after the ſaid <hi>Landaſſe,</hi> to do us Juſtice for the ſaid rude, and undecent words, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that the ſaid
<hi>Landaſse</hi> had preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded, in the name of the Kings Atturney, againſt the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny.</hi> Whereupon, in doing right upon the ſaid Requeſt, We the ſaid <hi>Anffrye,</hi> in the quality aforeſaid have taken and forced the ſaid <hi>De Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigny</hi> to tell the truth upon his oath, who hath told us, that truely he had <pb n="175" facs="tcp:121272:88"/> taken to party the ſaid Gentleman the Sheriff, but that he had not uſed theſe words, <hi>We ſhall meet with you well enough:</hi> which fault being conſidered, and becauſe it was witneſſed unto us by Maſter
<hi>William,</hi> Commiſſioner of the Regiſter of this Court, That the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny</hi> had ſpeaking unto the ſaid Gentleman the Sheriff, <hi>We ſhall meet with you well enough;</hi> and that there were here many perſons, which might have heard it. We have cauſed to come and to appear before us Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Geuffin Cavé, Claude Clavé, Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Vaignon,</hi> and <hi>Jean Servain</hi> Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies deputed Commiſſioners in this Juriſdiction here preſent; which after a Solemn oath taken by them, to ſpeak and bring the truth: Againſt whom the ſaid
<hi>De Cauvigny</hi> being thereupon asked, would not alledge any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and alſo, when he had purged them of all wonted objections: they have told us, witneſſed, and related unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly and with the ſame, and like depoſition upon their oath, that they had heard juſt now, the ſaid <hi>De Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigny,</hi> 
                     <pb n="176" facs="tcp:121272:89"/> ſpeaking unto his worſhip the Sheriff, when he had told him, that he took him to party, and that he had uſed theſe words, <hi>We ſhall meet with you well enough;</hi> being moved with anger, holding in his hands ſome Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which he did exhibit unto his Worſhip the Sheriff, uſing many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent jeſts and poſtures: which rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, witneſſes being conſidered, and moreover, becauſe the ſaid <hi>De Cavig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> committed many inſolences in this Court, in our preſence, and even when it was atteſted unto us, by Maſter <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Doublet</hi> Advocate: upon the as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of his advice, that the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> had been ſued in this Court for uſury by one <hi>Du Thil</hi> by name; We have Ordered, according to the advice of the Aſſiſtants, that the ſaid <hi>De Cauvigny,</hi> ſhall by reaſon of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, forthwith lay down and depoſe the ſaid amercements, and without any prejudice to his appeal, and that he ſhall be really and effectually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned: and moreover, that it ſhall be extraordinarily proceeded againſt <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <pb n="177" facs="tcp:121272:89"/> ſhall be meet, whereof the ſaid <hi>De Cauuigny</hi> obtained theſe Preſents.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Puchot</hi> and <hi>Marest,</hi> two Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnatures; the Copies being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the originall in Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here above, tranſcribed by me <hi>Jean Vienne,</hi> his Majeſties Purſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant in his Court of Parliament at <hi>Roan,</hi> at the Requeſt of the Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Exchange of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of this Citie, to be availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſerve him, as it ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them.
<date>The 9 of <hi>May,</hi> 1567.</date>
                     </signed>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed</hi> Vienne, <hi>with his Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnature.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <div type="body_of_document">
                     <head>Of the <hi>15</hi> day, <hi>1567,</hi> at <hi>Roan,</hi> in the Court of Parliament.</head>
                     <p>BEtween <hi>Jeſſé de Cauuigny</hi> Citizen Merchant, dwelling in this Citie of <hi>Roan,</hi> appealing from the Sheriff of the ſaid place, or from his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and otherwiſe intimated, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by Maſter <hi>Peter Sirette</hi> his Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:121272:90"/> of the one part, and <hi>James du Fay</hi> alſo Citizen Merchant living in the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> intimated in the appeal of the ſaid <hi>Cauvigny,</hi> and for his own part, appealing from the Prior and Conſuls eſtabliſhed for the Merchants in the ſaid Citie, by M. <hi>John Morin</hi> his Atturney, of the other part: and alſo between the ſaid Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls, plaintiffs, by way of Petition, to that end, that Inhibitions may be made unto the ſaid Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> and to his Lieutenants, to take notice of cauſes and matters concerning Commerce and Traffick of Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe granted and given to the ſaid Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls, by the Kings Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Orders given thereupon; <hi>Pierre Lachers</hi> Merchant, and the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney of the ſaid Merchants Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, being preſent, joyned with the ſaid <hi>de Cauvigny,</hi> and by M. <hi>Richard le Fae</hi> their Atturney, of the one part: and the ſaid Sheriff of <hi>Roan,</hi> Defendant againſt the Requeſt of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, asking and deſiring the <pb n="179" facs="tcp:121272:90"/> grant of another Requeſt, tending to that end, that Inhibition may be made to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls to take upon them any other notice of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but that which was given them by the Ordinance of their ordaining and eſtabliſhing, or to attempt any thing againſt the Order made by the King, and againſt the Ordinance of the Court enſued thereupon, by which they are prohibited to aſſume unto themſelves the notice of thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which are ariſen and ſhall ariſe from Merchandiſes ſold and bought for the publike neceſſities, and for the Kings ſubjects, though it be between Merchants; appearing by M. <hi>Peter Deſhayes</hi> his Atturney, of the other part. The Court, the parties being heard, and the Sentences being read, which were given as well by the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff or by his Lieutenant, as by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, containing the Amercements of the one and of the other part, hath made the Appeal, and the matter thereof, void, without any Amercements or Charges: And <pb n="180" facs="tcp:121272:91"/> for this cauſe, and for amending the Judgement, hath ſent back, and doth ſend back the cauſe &amp; matter betwixt the ſaid <hi>Cauvigny</hi> and <hi>Du Fay,</hi> before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, on the firſt day, that right may be done unto them, as it ſhall be meet: and hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off, and doth take of the Amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in which the ſaid <hi>Cauvigny</hi> and <hi>Du Fay,</hi> and the Sergeant alſo, were reſpectively amerced by the ſaid She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riff, Prior and Conſuls; unto the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution whereof, the receivers have been and ſhall be conſtrained, by all due and reaſonable ways.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given as above.</dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed</hi> de Boiſleueſque, <hi>with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignature.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="endorsement">
                     <p>And theſe words were endorſed: <hi>The ſum of ten pounds</hi> tournois, <hi>was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven back again, and reſtored unto the ſaid</hi> Grenier, <hi>by Maſter</hi> Nicholas Vaignon, <hi>Receiver of the Amercements in the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivalty of</hi> Roan. Which ſum he was condemned to reſtore, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in the other part.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:121272:91"/>
                  <p>IN the yeer of our Lord, 1568, on Munday the 11 of
<hi>October,</hi> in the Court, before us, <hi>John de Brevedent</hi> Eſquire, Counſellour unto the King our Lord, and Lieutenant-Generall in the Bayliffs Court of <hi>Roan:</hi> between <hi>John Peter</hi> priſoner and plaintiff, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be admitted into the Benefice of Ceſſion of goods, appearing by <hi>Tiregorge</hi> his Atturney, on the one part; and the Worſhipfull <hi>Stephen Dugard</hi> Merchant in this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> defendant againſt the ſaid Ceſſion, and withall Plaintiff, deſiring to be ſent back before the Prior and Conſuls of this ſaid Citie, appearing by <hi>le Mire</hi> his Atturney, of the other part. The parties being heard, the Bonds being read, and the Accounts brought in by the ſaid
<hi>Dugard</hi> and the Kings Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the ſaid Bailiffs Court, who hath ſaid, that the impriſonment of the ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> was by vertue of Bills of hand, and of Accounts acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls; <pb n="182" facs="tcp:121272:92"/> the moſt part whereof were made in the Citie of <hi>London:</hi> and the matter was between the parties about their Negotiations and Traffick, and the priviledges thereof: for that cauſe he intended not to hinder the ſaid renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. As for the ſaid <hi>Peter,</hi> that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to withſtand the removing of his Suit, becauſe the queſtion was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about Ceſſion of goods into which he pretended to be admitted; which was not under the notice and Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, We have ordered nevertheleſſe, that the ſaid
<hi>Dugard</hi> ſhall proceed afore us, and ſhall prohibite the ſaid Petition of Ceſſion of goods, from which the ſaid <hi>le Mire,</hi> in the ſaid name, hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, which appealing he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to take, and cauſe to be ſerved in due time: whereof the ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> obtained theſe Preſents.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Varin</hi> with his Subſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:121272:92"/>
                  <head>Of the <hi>4</hi> day of <hi>February, 1569.</hi> in the Court of Parliament at <hi>Roan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BEtween <hi>Stephen Dugard,</hi> appealing from the Bailiff of
<hi>Roan</hi> his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and anticipated, appearing by M. <hi>William Valdorg</hi> his Atturney, of the one part: and <hi>John Peter,</hi> priſoner in the priſon of the Bayliwick of <hi>Roan,</hi> intimated and anticipating by Maſter <hi>Richard le Fae</hi> his Atturney, on the other part. The Court, the parties being heard, and the Kings Atturney-Generall likewiſe, ſay, That it was ill, and to no other effect judged by the ſaid Bailiff of
<hi>Roan,</hi> or by his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: and well appealed by <hi>le Mire,</hi> and amending the ſaid judgement. The ſaid Court hath ſent, and doth ſend back again the ſaid parties, to appear eight days hence before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> to proceed in the matter, as it ſhall be meet.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <pb n="184" facs="tcp:121272:93"/> 
                     <hi>The Copies are compared with the Original.</hi>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>de Boiſleueſque,</hi> with his Subſignature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <div type="body_of_document">
                     <head>An Extract out of the Regiſter of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Worſhipfull the Prior and the Conſuls of the Merchants of
<hi>Roan,</hi> of what followeth.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <date>Wedneſday <hi>the</hi> 13 of Decemb.
1570.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>VVHereas <hi>John Bourgovin</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, living at
<hi>Orleans,</hi> obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of us Warrant, and the Kings Letters-Patents in form of Debites, he being preſent in his own perſon, hath cauſed to be warned <hi>Richard Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> Merchant, living in Saint
<hi>Chriſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> neer <hi>Montfort</hi> in the Sherivalty of
<hi>Pontanton,</hi> and <hi>Ponteaudemer</hi> within the Bayliwick of
<hi>Roan,</hi> alſo preſent, to ſave or amend a default which the ſaid
<hi>Bourgovin</hi> had got againſt the ſaid <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> the 25 of
<hi>December</hi> laſt, and to ſee himſelf condemned to pay him the ſum of 25 <hi>
                           <abbr>l.</abbr> tournois,</hi> for which he ſaid
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:121272:93"/> that the ſaid <hi>Pillon</hi> had remained de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>btour unto him upon ſome Accounts made by the ſaid <hi>Pillon,</hi> between them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon a day paſt, for a certain quantity of Merchandiſe of Wines, which he had formerly ſold and ſent to the ſaid <hi>Pillon:</hi> Since the which Accounts, he ſaid that he had ſent a Kilderkin of Wine, which he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give him, upon the making of the ſaid Accounts. The ſaid <hi>Pillon</hi> conſidering the Allegation made, that it was for Merchandiſe ſent, and that the ſaid pretended Accounts were made in his houſe, he hath acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged it, and hath demanded to be ſent back again afore his ordinary Judge, though he confeſſed himſelf to be a Merchant: which removing of the Suit was withſtood and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the ſaid
<hi>Bourgovin,</hi> maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that he ought to proceed afore us, ſince the difference was about Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe between Merchants. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, advice being taken of many Merchants being then preſent, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the quality and condition of <pb n="186" facs="tcp:121272:94"/> Merchants of both the ſaid parties, and that the ſaid <hi>Pillon</hi> is reſiding within the Bailywick of this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> and ſeeing the Warrants and the Kings Letters Pattents in form of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitis,</hi> obtained by the ſaid <hi>Bourgouin;</hi> We have denied the ſaid removing of the ſuit, unto the ſaid <hi>Pillon;</hi> which was demanded by him, and have ſaid, that he was bound to anſwer before us in the ſaid Action; from which the ſaid <hi>Pillon</hi> hath declared that he did appeal, for which cauſe the ſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have reſpectively choſen their lodgings. To wit, the ſaid <hi>Pillon</hi> his own in the houſe of Maſter <hi>Heultes</hi> Atturney in the Court of Parliament, and the ſaid <hi>Bourgouin</hi> at Maſter <hi>Charls Drovets</hi> Merchant, living in Saint <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents Pariſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <opener>
                              <signed>
                                 <hi>CHarles</hi> by the Grace of God King of <hi>France,</hi>
                              </signed>
                              <salute>to all them that ſhall ſee theſe preſents, Greeting.</salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>We give you to underſtand, that <hi>Richard Pillon</hi> appearing this day in the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Office of our Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <pb n="187" facs="tcp:121272:94"/> and appealing from the Prior and Conſuls of this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> by Maſter <hi>Peter Heultes</hi> his Atturney, of the one part; and <hi>John Bourgouin</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, living for this preſent at <hi>Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouillet</hi> preſent in perſon, and by <hi>Tulles Mare</hi> his Atturney, aſſiſted by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Jean Du Hamel</hi> his Councell, of the other part. It was appointed or ordered, when the Advocate and the Atturney of the ſaid
<hi>Pillon</hi> have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that they found no valid cauſe, for which they ſhould maintain the ſaid appeal, and the conſent of our Atturney Generall concurring with it; and the ſaid parties appearing as before: that the ſaid appeal was made voyd, by paying ſeventy five <hi>ſols</hi> amercement; the ſentence from which it is appealed, in date of the 13. day of
<hi>December,</hi> 1570. ſhall take its effect, and ſhall be performed in every point, according to the form and tenour thereof, notwithſtanding oppoſitions and appeals whatſoever: the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are ſent back again before the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and Conſuls, to proceede between <pb n="188" facs="tcp:121272:95"/> themſelves according to the ſaid ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, and as it ſhall be meet.</p>
                           <p>And moreover the ſaid <hi>Pillon</hi> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff in the appeal, is condemned to the charges of the cauſe, and action of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, the taxation thereof being reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to our ſaid Court. Moreover we do command the firſt Purſuivant of our Court, or any of the Kings Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants deſired thereof to execute this preſent Ordinance, as much as it ſhall belong to him, and as his Office ſhall require, and as far as the ſaid
<hi>Bourgouin</hi> ſhall require of him fully and intirely according to the form and tenour thereof, We give him authority ſo to do: we command all our Juſtices, Officers, and Subjects to obey him in ſo doing. In witneſſe whereof we have cauſed our ſeal to be put to theſe preſents.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <dateline>
                                 <hi>Given at</hi> Roan
<date>
                                    <hi>the</hi> 5. <hi>day of February in the year of our Lord</hi> 1573. <hi>and the thirteenth yeer of our Reign.</hi>
                                 </date>
                              </dateline>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </div>
                  <div type="seal">
                     <p>And upon the turning of the Labell theſe words are written.
<hi>By the King.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>De Boiſleueſque,</hi> with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignature, <pb n="189" facs="tcp:121272:95"/> ſealed with a double Label with the ſeal of yellow Wax.</signed>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>Of the ſeventeenth day of Octob. <hi>1573.</hi> at
<hi>Roan</hi> in the Chamber appointed during the vacations.</head>
                  <p>BEtween <hi>Stephen du Venon,</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the Prior and Conſuls eſtabliſhed in this City of <hi>Roan,</hi> and anticipated, appearing by Maſter <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn le Roy</hi> his Atturney of the one part, and
<hi>Iſabell le Noir</hi> Widdow of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed <hi>Peter Chevey</hi> in his life Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, and then living at <hi>Orleans,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and Anticipating, <hi>Franceſſe le Noir,</hi> being preſent, the widdow of the deceaſed <hi>Fremin des Fourneaux</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a Merchant, and of
<hi>Orleans,</hi> and by Maſter <hi>John Morin</hi> her Atturney of the other part, whereas <hi>De la Fay</hi> Lawyer for the ſaid intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and anticipating, hath required and demanded, that the plaintiff in the appeal ſhould propoſe the cauſes or reaſons of his appeal, or elſe that
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:121272:96"/> default might be granted unto him with ſuch profit as the caſe doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. <hi>Le Roy</hi> Atturney for the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff in the appeal, hath ſaid, That as for the appeal, he would ſay nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude nothing about it, but that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conſulted upon the matter, he had found by his Councell, that his appeal ought to be changed into an oppoſition, and that to this effect, and for that purpoſe he had ſet letters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſeal, beſeeching the Court to accept of his ſaid letters, iſſued out by a Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p>And it was ſaid by the ſaid <hi>La Fay,</hi> that the ſaid
<hi>Le Roy</hi> upon juſt reaſon will not plead for the ſaid appeal, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth appeal without any grievance from which the appeal muſt reſult, becauſe his bond was turned into a deed, judged by the Prior and Conſuls, his cauſes of oppoſition on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted, unto which he was to be received upon depoſiting and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down the money due. Therefore he needed not any other Letters, but he ought rather to alleadge his reaſons
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:121272:96"/> for his appeal, or elſe the appeal to be voyd, and the ſentence confirmed with charges, and in caſe of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the parties ſhould be ſent back again before the Prior and the Conſuls, before which he maintained that they ought to be ſent back, ſince the queſtion and difference was about Merchandiſes, and that he maketh no other acquittance to appear, but what is endorſed upon his bond. The ſaid <hi>Le Roy</hi> inſiſting upon his Declaration ſaying, that he forbiddeth the ſending back of the cauſe to the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, conſidering the remoteneſſe of the place of his habitation, and that he cannot be removed, and taken off from his ordinary Juriſdiction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which he deſired to be ſent back to proceede in the oppoſition: in the diſcourſe whereof he proteſted to make uſe of his acquaintances, and to tell and produce all his reaſons, and cauſes of oppoſition.</p>
                  <p>When the Advocate and the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney of the Plaintiff in the appeal could not tell any valide cauſe, or <pb n="192" facs="tcp:121272:97"/> reaſon to maintain it: the Court hath made it and doth make it voyd: hath ordered and doth order, that the thing from which it is appealed, ſhall take its full and entire effect; and hath condemned and doth condemn, the Plaintiff in the appeal, unto 100. <hi>ſols,</hi> for the King, and to the charges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Intimated, and hath ſent back, and doth ſend back, the parties on the firſt Court day, before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of this City of
<hi>Roan,</hi> to proceed upon the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as it ſhall be meet.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                     </dateline> 
                     <hi>The Copies being compared with the Originall.</hi>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>De Boiſleueſque,</hi> with his Subſignature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <p>IN the year of our Lord 1577. the 12. day of <hi>November</hi> in the new-Caſtle, before us <hi>Francis Aviſſe</hi> Lord of
<hi>Songeons</hi> Sheriff of the ſaid place: Vpon the complaint made by
<hi>Michael Herlenc</hi> priſoner in the priſons of this place; againſt
<hi>Jean Bricquot</hi> the Kings Sergeant in the ſaid City of <hi>Roan;</hi>
                     <pb n="193" facs="tcp:121272:97"/> becauſe he had impriſoned the ſaid <hi>Herlenc</hi> at the requeſt of <hi>Graffard</hi> by name, a Merchant living in
<hi>Roan,</hi> for the ſum of 100. <abbr>l.</abbr> for one part, and of 27.
<abbr>l.</abbr> ten <hi>ſols,</hi> for another part: which he ſhould ſay to be due unto the ſaid <hi>Graffard</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Herlenc,</hi> for the ſale of wine: the ſaid impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment made by vertue of a certain obligation acknowledged before the Prior and Conſuls of the ſaid place in
<hi>Roan,</hi> the 25. of <hi>September</hi> laſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which there was no attachment of the honourable the Bayliff of <hi>Caux,</hi> nor of us neither. Therefore he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired the ſaid Warrant to be made voyde, and the ſaid
<hi>Herlenc</hi> to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and to be put out of the ſaid priſon, with the intereſt and charges. When we had heard the ſaid Serge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant thereupon, who hath confeſſed, that he made the ſaid impriſonment by vertue of the ſaid Obligation, without any attachment; we have declared the ſaid execution and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant voyde and annulled; and made an inhibition unto the ſaid Sergeant, <pb n="194" facs="tcp:121272:98"/> to make any more impriſonments of ſuch perſons reſorting, and Oſtagers of this Juriſdiction, without our at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment, or that of the honourable the Bayliff, upon the penalty of
100. <abbr>l.</abbr> amercement; and we do order for this preſent, that the ſaid <hi>Herlenc</hi> ſhall be delivered out of the ſaid priſons, and that the goods taken upon exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, by the ſaid Sergeant, ſhall be reſtored by the ſaid Sergeants, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid <hi>Herlenc,</hi> except the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his intereſts and charge, which to obtain, he ſhall (if he thinketh good) cauſe the ſaid <hi>Graffard</hi> to come before us: unto which end a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant was granted to him; and the firſt Sergeant is commanded to put theſe preſents in execution.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Dated as above.</dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Aviſſe, &amp; Lorbec</hi> with their Subſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natures.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <div type="body_of_document">
                     <pb n="195" facs="tcp:121272:98"/>
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Of the</hi> 20. <hi>day December</hi>
1577.</date> 
                           <hi>at</hi> Roan <hi>in the Regiſters Office of the Court of Parliament.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>BEtween <hi>Peter Graffard</hi> Citizen of <hi>Roan,</hi> being joyned with him, the Atturney of the Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls of this ſaid City, and the Kings Atturney Generall, appealing from Maſter <hi>Francis Aviſſe,</hi> the Sheriff of the New-Caſtle, all appearing; to wit, the ſaid <hi>Graffard,</hi> by Maſter <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an le Tellier</hi> his Atturney, aſſiſted with Maſter <hi>William Prin</hi> his Councell, of the one part, and the ſaid Atturney of the Merchants by Maſter <hi>William le Fae</hi> his Atturney, aſſiſted by Maſter <hi>Peter Cadyot</hi> his Councell likewiſe of the one part, and the ſaid <hi>Aviſſe</hi> the Sheriff, intimated in the appeal, and taken to party, being preſent, and by Maſter <hi>Nicholas Guillot</hi> his Atturney, aſſiſted by Maſter
<hi>James Lermitte</hi> his Councell, of the other part. It was appointed with the conſent of the ſaid <pb n="196" facs="tcp:121272:99"/> parties appearing, as above; that the ſaid appeal, and that from which it was appealed, ſhould be made voyd, and by reforming the Judgement and ſentence, that the parties ſhould be diſcharged of the ſuite without any charges or intereſts of either part; and it was ordered that the ſentences of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls ſhall be put in execution according to the forme contained in the Ordinance of their Ordaining, and without being bound to take any attachments of the Judges of the places.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed <hi>De Boiſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſque</hi> with his Subſignature.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="judgment">
                     <opener>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>HEnry</hi> by the Grace of God, King of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Poland,</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <salute>to all thoſe that ſhall ſee theſe preſents, Greeting.</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>There being preſented this day in our Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Cauſe of <hi>Peter Allaine</hi> Citizen Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant of <hi>Roan,</hi> appealing from Maſter <hi>John du Tot,</hi> Lieutenant to the Sheriff
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:121272:99"/> of <hi>Caudebec</hi> in the ſea Court of <hi>Cany.</hi> The Atturney of the Prior and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls of the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> being joyned with the ſaid <hi>Allaine;</hi> likewiſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the ſaid
<hi>Du Tot:</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Allaine</hi> requiring the grant of a requeſt tending to the end that right may be done upon the principall, by judging the appeal, and to the ſaid principall Plaintiff, by an execution for the ſum of 29. crowns, two third parts of a crown, and ſeven
<hi>ſols</hi> ſix <hi>deniers;</hi> appearing by Maſter <hi>Nicholas du Queſnay,</hi> and <hi>Richard le Faé</hi> their Atturnies, of the one part; and <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las le Clerc</hi> intimated, and to the ſaid principall oppoſing himſelf, and the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> alſo intimated, and taken to party in his own particular name, and defendants againſt the ſaid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, by Maſter <hi>William Hallé,</hi> and <hi>Robert Arondell</hi> their Atturney, of the other. <hi>Prin</hi> for the Plaintiffs in the appeal hath ſaid, that their appeal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulteth and proceedeth from a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt errour in caſe of right, committed by the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> Lieutenant; and the <pb n="198" facs="tcp:121272:100"/> ſaid Plaintiffs in the appeal are not willing that this cauſe ſhould be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in a publike Audience: he hath offered an expedient out of the Court without ſuing, to make the appeal; and that from which it is appealed, voyd; and by the deciding the principall, that the ſaid <hi>Clerc,</hi> and <hi>Du Tot,</hi> might be condemned to the payment of 29. crowns, two thirds of a crown, ſeven <hi>ſols</hi> ſix
<hi>deniers,</hi> for the which ſum the ſaid <hi>Allaine</hi> had required and cauſed execution to be made upon the taking of many dead and alive
<hi>Mamps;</hi> which goods the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> had abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively cauſed to be put again into the poſſeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Le Clerc:</hi> the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> Judge <hi>a quo,</hi> pretending that the ſaid <hi>Allaine</hi> had no Authority to cauſe the ſentence to be given by the ſaid Prior and Conſuls upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſance or acknowledgement of the bill of the hand, and of the bond of the ſaid <hi>Le Clerc,</hi> containing the ſaid 29. crowns, two thirds of a crown, and 7.
<hi>ſols</hi> 6. <hi>deniers,</hi> to be put in execution, except he had obtained <pb n="199" facs="tcp:121272:100"/> of the ſaid Sheriff <hi>De Caudebec,</hi> or of him <hi>Du Tot</hi> his Lieutenant an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment to that effect; which is an errour in the fact and in Law, becauſe it is manifeſt <hi>Notorietate facti permanen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</hi> That the Warrants, Sentences, and Judgements of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls are to be put in execution within all the Precincts of this Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, without asking of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Judges of any of the places, any <hi>placet,</hi> leave or attachments for that purpoſe, by the means of which er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, upon which the ſentence and Ordinance of the ſaid
<hi>Du Tot</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, is grounded: the ſaid <hi>Allaine</hi> would be like to loſe his ſaid debt: the ſaid <hi>Clerc</hi> having been put again into the poſſeſſion of his goods, taken upon the execution, which he hath ſince alienated, and ſo became inſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; by the means whereof by the ſaid expedient, the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> and <hi>Le Clerc</hi> ſhould be condemned <hi>in ſolidum,</hi> to pay unto the ſaid <hi>Allaine</hi> the ſaid ſum with charges and intereſts; which expedient was accepted of by the ſaid <pb n="200" facs="tcp:121272:101"/> 
                        <hi>Le Clerc,</hi> and not by the ſaid
<hi>Du Tot,</hi> and therefore the ſaid <hi>Prin</hi> would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and alleadge his cauſes of appeal, and ſo conclude upon the principall. Whereupon <hi>Iſnel</hi> for the ſaid <hi>Le Clerc</hi> hath ſaid, That he did perſiſt in the Declaration made by him (out of the Court) that he accepted of the ſaid expedient, and by <hi>Du Vinier</hi> the elder for the ſaid <hi>Du Tot:</hi> that for his own part he would not (and for a juſt cauſe) accept of that expedient for his particular, becauſe it would not be reaſonable, that he, the ſaid <hi>Du Tot,</hi> who is a Judge, being no wayes inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed in the cauſe, ſhould be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>in ſolidum,</hi> to pay the ſaid ſum, for the ſaid <hi>Le Clerc,</hi> yet nevertheleſſe that the ſaid <hi>Du Tot,</hi> would willingly upon a ſentence againſt him, the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution whereof ſhould be forborn and ſtayed, untill ſufficient enquiry was made upon the ſaid <hi>Le Clerc,</hi> and untill he be found and declared inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable; and moreover to do more then he is bound to do, he would yeeld unto half the charges of the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:121272:101"/> cauſe of appeal; which he maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be more then reaſonable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is greatly to be excuſed, as having not ever known or heard, that there had been any Ordinances or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letters Pattents or Ordinances of Parliament, which had declared the Prior and Conſuls more priviledged, than the ordinary Judges, whoſe Warrants, Sentences, and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, cannot be put in execution beyond their Precincts and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without obtaining to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe attachments of the ordinary Judges, within the Precincts of whom they will require, and cauſe the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution thereof to be ſerved by thoſe means he hath concluded to the ends of an abſolution, and that he might be freed, in caſe the ſaid
<hi>Allaine</hi> would not accept of his profer, and it was ſaid and maintained by the ſaid <hi>Prin,</hi> for the ſaid <hi>Allaine,</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> is altogether inexcuſable, having erred in matter of fact and of Law, <hi>In facto &amp; in Jure,</hi> and by conſequence made the cauſe his own; the ſaid <pb n="202" facs="tcp:121272:102"/> 
                        <hi>Prin</hi> perſiſting to maintain, that the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> is to be condemned in <hi>ſolidum,</hi> and in body with the ſaid <hi>Clerc; Factus non ſolvendo,</hi> who is made inſolvable; againſt whom the ſaid
<hi>Allaine</hi> hath no more means to get himſelf to be paid, by reaſon of the deed and fault of the ſaid <hi>Du Tot,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding to theſe ends, and asking char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and the intereſts.</p>
                     <p>And it was ſaid by our Atturney-Generall, that the oppoſition made by the ſaid <hi>Clerc,</hi> upon whom the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſerved, grounding his oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the fault of not having got an Attachment. That the Sentences of the Prior and Conſuls are to be put in execution within all Precincts of this Juriſdiction, without any
<hi>Pareatis</hi> or Attachment. And the cauſe upon the ſaid oppoſition being preſented before the ſaid <hi>Du Tot</hi> Lieutenant, he hath under that colour, <hi>malè conſultus,</hi> being ill adviſed, made the execution void, and reſtored the ſaid party whoſe goods were executed into the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof; who, as the plaintiff in
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:121272:102"/> the appeal, doth plead, <hi>Factus eſt non ſolvendo,</hi> is made unable to pay, unſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable; in which the ſaid
<hi>Du Tot</hi> hath too groſly erred, and <hi>fecit litem ſuam,</hi> made the ſuit and cauſe his own. Therefore the ſaid Atturney-Generall adhereth unto the plea, to the ends and concluſions of the ſaid Plaintiffs in the appeal. We give therefore to underſtand, that our ſaid Court by its Ordinance and Judgement, the parties being heard, together with our Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney-Generall, hath made and doth make the ſaid appeal, and that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from which it is appealed, void; and amercing the Judge, hath ordered and doth order, that within ſixteen days, for all prefixions and delays, the ſaid <hi>le Clerc</hi> who oppoſeth it, ſhall be bound to bring forth the goods taken of him upon execution; and that he ſhall be conſtrained to do it, by all due and reaſonable means, even by the impriſonment of his perſon: and in caſe of a refuſall, or of a delay in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, our ſaid Court hath from this very preſent time, condemned and <pb n="104" facs="tcp:121272:103"/> doth condemn the ſaid <hi>Du Tot,</hi> in his own particular name ſubſidiarily, in caſe of not bringing for the ſaid goods, to pay unto the ſaid <hi>Allaine</hi> the ſum for which the execution, which is now in debate, was deſired by the ſaid
<hi>Allaine,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Clerc</hi> Debtor and Defendant, to the charges for the ſaid <hi>Allaine,</hi> unto the day of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration made by him, That he aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto the way and expedient offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him by the Plaintiff in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, to the other charges ſince the ſaid Declaration to this preſent time, for the ſaid <hi>Allaine,</hi> ſave in all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and recompence of the ſaid <hi>Du Tot,</hi> againſt the ſaid <hi>Clerc,</hi> which our Court hath ordered at this very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, condemned by body to the ſaid recourſe concerning the principall ſum; and moreover hath condemned the ſaid <hi>le Clerc</hi> to the charges of the ſaid <hi>Du Tot.</hi> Beſides, we do command the firſt Purſuivant of our Court, or any of the Kings Sergeants, required thereof, to put this preſent Decree in execution, ſo far as it ſhall concern
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:121272:103"/> him to do, and as far as he ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to do by the ſaid <hi>Allain</hi> duely and fully, according to the form and tenour thereof; conſtraining all whom it ſhall concern to obey him, and which ſhall cauſe themſelves to be conſtrained, by all due and reaſonable ways: we give him authority and commiſſion ſo to do. We charge and command all our Juſtices, Officers and Subjects to obey him in ſo doing.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Given at</hi> Roan <hi>in our ſaid Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
                           <date>
                              <hi>the</hi> 17 <hi>day of</hi> March, <hi>in the yeer of the Lord</hi> 1593. <hi>and the</hi> 5 <hi>yeer of our Reign.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Signed by the Court, <hi>de Lintot</hi> with his Subſignature, and ſealed upon a double Label with yellow Wax, with a little counter-Seal of yellow Wax.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <p>IN the yeer of our Lord 1593. on <hi>Saturday</hi> the 27 day of
<hi>March,</hi> the Court then ſitting, being afore us <hi>John le Doux</hi> Eſquire, Counſellour unto the King, Lieutenant-Generall Civill in
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:121272:104"/> the Bayliwick of <hi>Roan,</hi> between the Worſhipfull M. <hi>James Febvrier</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour and creditour unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren under age and heirs of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull <hi>Bartholomew le Cuilier,</hi> plaintiff, and appearing by <hi>Richer</hi> his Atturney, of the one part; and the Worſhipfull <hi>Claudius le Cuiller</hi> Tutour of the ſaid under-aged, cited to declare unto the ſaid worſhipfull
<hi>Febvrier,</hi> if he had not received, or cauſed to be ſold, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to be put to profit for the ſaid under-aged, the number of 260 Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells and a half, of Salt <hi>Callais</hi> meaſure, belonging unto the ſaid under-aged, and put them into the hands of <hi>John Gryniers</hi> ſon of the deceaſed <hi>Charles Gryniers,</hi> in the ſaid <hi>Callais,</hi> according to the ſaid <hi>John Gryniers</hi> Letter and Accounts ſent from
13 day of <hi>June,</hi> 1587. or elſe to declare in whoſe hands the ſaid Salt was yet at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, upon proteſtation made by the ſaid the Worſhipfull <hi>Febvrier:</hi> in caſe of the negligence of the ſaid
<hi>le Cuillier</hi> Tutour, in putting the ſaid Salt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and of leaving it ſo long a ſpace of <pb n="207" facs="tcp:121272:104"/> time; and ſeeing that the Traffick was free with them at <hi>Deepes,</hi> by the means whereof, it was eaſie to put it off and to ſell it: That the ſaid prices and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation of the ſaid Salt, muſt be laid upon the ſaid
<hi>Cuillier;</hi> and that in caſe any loſſe thereof doth chance to hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, it ſhal be at the perils and intereſts of the ſaid
<hi>Cuillers</hi> his brother, and ſecurity for the ſaid <hi>Claudius;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Claudius Cuiller</hi> Tutour and Defendant, appearing by his eldeſt ſon, and by <hi>le Pueu</hi> his Atturney, of the other part. When the ſaid <hi>Cuillers</hi> had perſiſted to demand that the cauſe ſhould be ſent back, as he did demand it yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and proteſted that the ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by the ſaid <hi>Febvrier</hi> was of no validity, it was ſaid, That the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhall be and are ſent back again to the ſaid place on Munday next, to proceed upon the ſaid ſummoning, as it ſhall be meet.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Richer</hi> and <hi>Nephueu,</hi> with both their Subſignatures.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:121272:105"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Of the</hi> 4 <hi>day of</hi> December, 1597.</date> 
                        <hi>at</hi> Roan, <hi>in the Court of Parliament.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEtween <hi>Anthonie Solenne,</hi> calling himſelf the Deputy-Commiſſary unto the Treaſurer-generall of the States of
<hi>Flanders,</hi> plaintiff, by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the 30 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, tending to an Order for a Judge, by reaſon of the contention about Juriſdiction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Bayliff of <hi>Roan,</hi> or his Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and the Prior and Conſuls of this ſaid City, and in chief alſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiff for a Decree and a Diſtrein, in the hands of <hi>Nicholas Bailleul</hi> Citizen of the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> upon the ſum of 200 Crowns conſigned into his hands by <hi>Giles Fouan,</hi> to receive payment by the ſaid
<hi>Solenne</hi> of a great deal of money due unto him, by <hi>Daniel Loyſeleur,</hi> for the remainder upon accounts, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring by M.
<hi>Thierre des Mareſtz</hi> his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney, of the one part; and the ſaid
<hi>Giles Fouon</hi> a <hi>Fleming,</hi> Merchant here, by benefice of Inventory by his wife; <pb n="209" facs="tcp:121272:105"/> of the ſaid <hi>Loyſeur</hi> preſent in perſon, and by M. <hi>Nicholas le Cerf</hi> his Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, on the other part. <hi>Deſchamps</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard for the ſaid
<hi>Solenne,</hi> and <hi>Chreſtien</hi> for the ſaid <hi>Fouan,</hi> the Court hath changed and doth change the ſaid Ordinance into action; and that right may be done upon it, hath ſent back and doth ſend back the parties before the Prior and Conſuls of <hi>Roan:</hi> and inhibition is made unto the ſaid parties to treat elſewhere, upon the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of nullity of their proceedings, the charges being reſerved: and hath in the interim ordered and doth order, that the ſaid <hi>Fouan</hi> ſhall have a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe of the money ſtayed, upon giving ſecurity for the ſaid ſumme of 200 Crowns.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>The copie is compared with the Originall.</hi> Signed <hi>de Boiſleueſque</hi> with his Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnature.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="petition">
                  <div type="body_of_petition">
                     <pb n="210" facs="tcp:121272:106"/>
                     <head>To the Lords of the Parliament. <hi>The humble Petition of</hi> Francis le Tein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teurier <hi>Citizen of</hi> Roan, <hi>Priſoner in the Court.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                     <p>THat your Petitioner was arreſted on Tueſday the 9 of this inſtant moneth, according to the Extract of his impriſonment annexed hereunto, at the ſuit of <hi>Nicholas Larcanier</hi> Tutor in chief unto the children of <hi>Nicholas Godin,</hi> in his life Citizen of <hi>Roan,</hi> which are yet under age, for the ſum of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hundred threeſcore and five pounds <hi>tournois,</hi> according, and for the cauſes contained in the ſaid Extract, for and in the name of the ſaid chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren under age of the ſaid deceaſed <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din;</hi> although the ſaid <hi>Godin</hi> doth but repreſent any particular perſon, for buying the Petitioners debt at a rate more than juſt by half, as the Court ſhall know, by the Bills of hand and Cedulles inſerted into the accounts, by vertue of which he was made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner: <pb n="211" facs="tcp:121272:106"/> yet nevertheleſſe the ſaid Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner to prevent the detaining of his perſon in priſon, hath offered and doth offer unto the ſaid <hi>Larcanier,</hi> all and as much yeerly means as he can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe, which conſiſteth but in 50 <hi>
                           <abbr>l.</abbr> per annum,</hi> untill the end of his payment, having no ways to ſatisfie the debt: and moreover, that he hath a charge of two children upon his hands. For theſe cauſes, may it pleaſe you, my Lords, that the Petitioner may be enlarged and let out of priſon, with making over unto the ſaid
<hi>Larcanier</hi> a Letter of an Atturney of the ſaid 50 <hi>
                           <abbr>l.</abbr> per an.</hi> or elſe to ſee himſelf received and admitted to the Benefice of Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of goods; and to that end, to grant and give Warrant unto the ſaid Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, to call within few days the ſaid <hi>Larcanier</hi> before this Court, and you ſhall do well.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Signed</hi> le Teinturier <hi>and</hi> Cavé, <hi>for</hi> Bindel <hi>Atturney, with their Subſignatures.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="resolution">
                     <argument>
                        <p>And underneath the ſaid Petition, the following Ordinance is written.</p>
                     </argument>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let the Petitioner have his recourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:121272:107"/> the Prior and Conſuls, that right may be done to him, as it ſhall be meet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given at <hi>Roan</hi> in the Parliament, <date>the
11 day of <hi>April,</hi>
1619.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="citation">
                     <p>And lower: <hi>The</hi> 12 <hi>day of the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and yeer, at the requeſt and petition of the ſaid</hi> le Teinteur
<hi>aforenamed; and by vertue of the preſent Petition and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, I have cited the ſaid</hi> Larcanier <hi>here alſo named, ſpeaking to him in his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in the place of his habitation at</hi> Roan, <hi>to appear to morrow morning, before the Worſhipfull Prior and the Conſuls of the Merchants of</hi> Roan, <hi>to be heard upon the ends of theſe preſents.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Done by me Purſuivant in the Court, underſigned: and I have given a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie of the Warrant, in the preſence of
<hi>Martin Bouchart,</hi> and of others. <hi>Levent.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>Of the <hi>10.</hi> of Aprill <hi>1619.</hi> in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Edict in the Parliament at <hi>Roan.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BEtween <hi>William de Hammerville</hi> Merchant, Citizen of
<hi>Roan,</hi> cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor unto <hi>Peter de Namps,</hi> Plaintiff by
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:121272:107"/> a requeſt preſented by him unto the Court the 11. day of <hi>December</hi> laſt: That, by reaſon of the appeal from the 100.
<hi>ſols</hi> amercement Judged, and given againſt him by the Prior and Conſuls the 10. day of <hi>December</hi> 1618 for the pretended transferring and removing of Juriſdiction and of the contention of Juriſdiction between the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of Merchants in the ſaid <hi>Roan;</hi> and the Sheriff of the ſaid place, for keeping a day for accompts of the money raiſed out of the ſale of the moveables and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes of the ſaid
<hi>de Namps</hi> diſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the requeſt of the ſaid
<hi>Hammer-ville;</hi> by vertue of a ſentence of the ſaid Prior, and Conſuls; There was a Warrant was granted to him, to cite all the creditors of the ſaid <hi>De Namps</hi> oppoſing themſelvs to the ſaid making of accompts, to be ordered concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Judges. The ſaid <hi>De Hammerville</hi> appearing in perſon, and by Maſter <hi>Anthony Clovet</hi> his Atturney of the one part, <hi>Peter le Roux, Jean le Court</hi> the younger, and
<hi>Charles Coaſture</hi> alſo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors <pb n="214" facs="tcp:121272:108"/> unto the ſaid <hi>de Namps</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves about the ſaid money cited upon the ſaid Requeſt, and the defendants appearing, to wit, the ſaid
<hi>Le Court,</hi> and <hi>Conſture</hi> by Maſter <hi>James de la Ruelle:</hi> and the ſaid <hi>le Roux,</hi> by Mr. <hi>James Baillard</hi> their Atturnies of the other part; in the preſence of the ſaid Prior and Conſuls of the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of the ſaid <hi>Roan,</hi> having preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves in the cauſe, to demand the ſending back thereof into their Juriſdiction, appearing by Mr. <hi>Ambroſe Marc,</hi> their Atturney of the other part: the Court ſitting in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Edict; the parties being heard, and alſo the Kings Atturney Generall, hath made and doth make voyd the appeal and the Contents thereof, and amending and redreſſing the Judgement and ſentence, hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged and doth diſcharge the ſaid <hi>de Hammerville,</hi> of the amercement made by the ſaid ſentence; and doing right upon the ſaid <hi>Warrant,</hi> hath ſent back and doth ſend back the parties before the ſaid Prior and Conſuls, to <pb n="215" facs="tcp:121272:108"/> be proceeded between them as it ſhall be meet and fit.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given as above: </hi>
                     </dateline> 
                     <hi>and there is written beneath; the Coppies were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the Originall.</hi>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>De Boiſleueſque</hi> with his ſubſignature, and a flouriſh.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="document">
                  <head>An Extract out of the Regiſters of the Court of Parliament.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Petition preſented by the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or and the Conſuls of this City of <hi>Roan:</hi> tending to the end, that it may be permitted unto them to put in Print aſwell the Declaration, and Ordinance of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining and eſtabliſhing of their Juriſdiction and of a Common place for Merchants in this ſaid City, of the moneth of <hi>March</hi> 1556. as alſo an Ordinance of the Court made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the approving of the ſaid Declaration; an Ordinance, and other Letters Pattents, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances and Declarations of the enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſaid Juriſdiction, Ordinances, and Orders made afterwards thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that in time hereafter, there may be nothing undertaken to the prejudice of the <pb n="216" facs="tcp:121272:109"/> ſaid Juriſdiction under pretext of being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thereof.</p>
                  <p>The Court having ſeen, and peruſed this Petition, the Coppies of the ſaid Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Letters Pattents, Ordinances and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the Concluſion of the Kings Atturney Generall, and the Councellor deputed for that purpoſe being heard; hath with the conſent of the ſaid Atturney Generall, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and doth permit unto the ſaid Prior and Conſuls to put in Print the ſaid Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, Letters Pattents, Ordinances, and Orders, to ſerve and to be availeable unto them, as it ſhall concern them.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Given in the ſaid Court of</hi> Roan
<date>
                           <hi>the ſecond day of</hi> July <hi>one thouſand ſix hundred and nineteen.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>De Boiſleueſque.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Printed according to Order.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
